<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Documents on CAA/SSLA</title><link>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/</link><description>Recent content in Documents on CAA/SSLA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Letter to the members of the SIG</title><link>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/letter_members_bid/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/letter_members_bid/</guid><description>Dear colleagues,
You are receiving this message because you are listed on the mailing list as a potential member of a CAA Special Interest Group (SIG) &amp;lsquo;Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology&amp;rsquo;.
This year at the CAA 2020 in Oxford we will submit a bid to have this group accepted as an official SIG of the CAA. In a preliminary enquiry to the CAA, we were told that we should illustrate in the bid that we already have support, preferably by compiling a list of archaeologists expressing their interest in the new SIG.</description></item><item><title>Special interest group proposal</title><link>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/caa_proposal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/caa_proposal/</guid><description>Dear honourable members of the CAA Steering Committee,
With this letter, we would like to express our intention to establish a CAA Special Interest Group for Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology (SIG-SSLA) under the auspices of the CAA. The idea for this SIG was developed in 2018 in a session on R as an archaeological tool. Out of this event and the resulting discussions, it was proposed to form such a Special Interest Group to create a permanent platform for the exchange and discussion of ideas and to develop the practical use of R for archaeological applications.</description></item><item><title>Twitter guidelines</title><link>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/twitter_guidelines/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://joeroe.io/sslarch.github.io/documents/twitter_guidelines/</guid><description>We can collect here what we would like to use Twitter for dissemination of new packages, releases etc. dissemination of actions planned by the SIG point of contact for outsiders amplify and support the work done by individuals and other collectives that relates to our core mission generally promote scientific computing as a cool thing to do 8-) Curation rolling by a team of volunteers gathering of ideas by all members of the SIG Rules do not post or share harmful, offensive or illegal content, including that which is racist, homophobic, transphobic, sexist, ableist or which hatefully targets a religious group do not share personal information about any specific individual without their express consent (i.</description></item></channel></rss>