<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on CAA/SSLA</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on CAA/SSLA</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sslarch.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Martin Hinz</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Sophie Schmidt</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Clemens Schmid</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>44th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2025_02_07/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2025_02_07/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="social-media">Social Media&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>archaeo.social&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a> (maintained by Joe Roe and Zack Batist) keeps growing, with more working groups using it (e.g. HAAM - &lt;a href="https://haam-community.github.io">https://haam-community.github.io&lt;/a>, SPAAM - &lt;a href="https://www.spaam-community.org">https://www.spaam-community.org&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The financial costs to maintain and extend the mastodon and matrix servers currently exceed the level of donations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Users should consider donating: &lt;a href="https://opencollective.com/archaeosocial">https://opencollective.com/archaeosocial&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Potential questions from the SIG SSLA to the CAA:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>(1) Could the CAA suport the SIG financially to enable us to donate to archaeo.social?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>(2) Would the CAA itself be interested in using chat.archaeo.social?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>(2) must first be discussed with Joe: The growth of archaeo.social comes with technical and social (legal?) challenges, e.g. because of content moderation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>bluesky&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>43rd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2025-01-08/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2025-01-08/</guid><description>&lt;p>4 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recap-noteworthy-developments-in-2024-in-and-around-the-sig">Recap: Noteworthy developments in 2024 in and around the SIG&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Change in chat software. We moved from Slack to &lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Invited talks. Nicolas Frerebeau introduced the tesselle R package suite in October: &lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Emerging resources:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A list for software funding opportunities: &lt;a href="https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52">https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A list of Diamond Open Access journals: &lt;a href="https://diamond.open-archaeo.info">https://diamond.open-archaeo.info&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>SIG Projects. Reviving old, archaeological research software with focus on the TFQA suite: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="caa2025-conference">CAA2025 conference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It currently seems as if the SIG&amp;rsquo;s session on APIs and DSLs got enough submissions and will come together: &lt;a href="https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S52">https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S52&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The conference program is still unclear, but is currently announced to extend over five days (5-9 May)!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="ideasplans-for-the-sig-in-2025">Ideas/Plans for the SIG in 2025&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Invited talks by Shawn Graham (already invited, needs scheduling) and Emily Coco (Sébastien Plutniak offered to ask her)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proposal by James Allison: Work committedly on the TFQAR project and present the progress in a session at CAA2026? Maybe with a focus on spatial data analysis.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bridge our Mastodon account to Bluesky and be more visible on social media: &lt;a href="https://archaeo.social/@CAA_SSLA">https://archaeo.social/@CAA_SSLA&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A new survey to optimize our meeting time (will be announced separately)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="various-news">Various news&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The French CAA chapter is officially confirmed: &lt;a href="https://caafrance.hypotheses.org">https://caafrance.hypotheses.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sébastien heard about ongoing work on reviving &lt;em>Le Stratifiant&lt;/em>, a software tool for archaeological stratigraphy modelling: &lt;a href="https://abp.hypotheses.org/files/2017/07/2010-actes-Vienne.pdf">https://abp.hypotheses.org/files/2017/07/2010-actes-Vienne.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PhD Position in Oslo: &lt;a href="https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/271130/doctoral-research-fellowship-in-archaeology">https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/271130/doctoral-research-fellowship-in-archaeology&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-february-5-2025">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, February 5, 2025&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>42nd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-11-06/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-11-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="general-exchange">General exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA 2025 conference
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Please consider to submit an abstract to our main session on computational interfaces (APIs/DSLs) and advertise it among your colleagues: &lt;a href="https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S52">https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S52&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nobody has so far taken the initative for the proposed TFQA workshop/hackathon (see the minutes from our previous meeting: &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-10-02)">https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-10-02)&lt;/a>, but multiple SIG members have offered to join as participants if it was to happen. Please consider organizing it - the SIG would not leave you hanging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lisa Steinmann advertised a CAA2025 session on &amp;ldquo;Comparing the Incomparable: Managing and Analyzing Data from Heterogeneous Sources in Archaeological Research&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S17">https://2025.caaconference.org/call-for-papers/session-list/#S17&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Diamond Archaeology
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zack Batist introduced a new website project listing Diamond Open Access journals in Archaeology: &lt;a href="https://diamond.open-archaeo.info">https://diamond.open-archaeo.info&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feel free to join the project and the ongoing discussion on how to further develop this resource&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The SIG SSLA decided to advertise it on their Mastodon account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack also created a new GitHub organization for this and other projects (&lt;a href="https://github.com/open-archaeo">https://github.com/open-archaeo&lt;/a>) to where he eventually also wants to move the repo behind the original open-archeo website (&lt;a href="https://open-archaeo.info">https://open-archaeo.info&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Funding sources list
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A discussion in a previous meeting (&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-09-04">https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-09-04&lt;/a>) let to the creation of a list of funding resources for scientific open source software development: &lt;a href="https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52">https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As these opportunities are prone to change we decided not to present or organize them beyond the GitHub discussion thread where they currently are&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Computational Archaeology Discord Community
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Reminder that this network exists as well - it is closely related to the goals of the SIG SSLA: &lt;a href="https://book.archnetworks.net/#Discord">https://book.archnetworks.net/#Discord&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison&amp;rsquo;s LDen
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>James started the translation work of specific TFQA functions: &lt;a href="https://github.com/jallison7/LDen">https://github.com/jallison7/LDen&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He asked for feedback on performance issues and multiple SIG members offered to look into the code&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwindling numbers
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Attendance at the SIG SSLA meetings is low right now. Ideas to improve that:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Advertise on the Computational Archaeology Discord&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Invite back former regulars&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Invite more female speakers to our presentation format&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-dezember-4-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, Dezember 4, 2024&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We invited an external speaker, but at the time of writing these minutes we already know that they are not available for this meeting. More information will follow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>41th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-10-02/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-10-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>4 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sig-ssla-projects">SIG-SSLA Projects&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Project TFQA:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Progress:&lt;/strong> Significant progress has been made, thanks to Jim. He has implemented the first function, which could serve as the foundation for developing this into a complete package. There is a comment in the TFQA repository (Issue #3) with a link to Jim&amp;rsquo;s code.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Next Steps:&lt;/strong> Please review the code and work towards structuring it into a package. Follow the provided example to expand functionality and increase the project&amp;rsquo;s scope.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Task:&lt;/strong> Compile a &amp;ldquo;correlation table&amp;rdquo; comparing functionalities across &lt;strong>Tesselle&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>base R&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>TFQA&lt;/strong>, and other relevant packages. This will help us assess what functionality already exists and identify areas for further development.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Project: Session for CAA2025
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Session Update:&lt;/strong> The session has been accepted, and the Call for Papers (CfP) is expected to be released tomorrow.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Action Item:&lt;/strong> Consider contributing a talk on APIs and DSLs (Domain-Specific Languages) to this session.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Timeline:&lt;/strong> The CfP will likely close at the end of October or early November, so no immediate action is required before our next meeting. Keep the deadline in mind.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Project: Workshop for CAA2025
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Proposal:&lt;/strong> Sophie has proposed organizing an SSLA workshop or hackathon at CAA 2025, with a focus on advancing TFQA development.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Target Audience:&lt;/strong> This workshop would be aimed at more experienced programmers and would offer a hybrid format, allowing for remote participation for those unable to attend in person in Athens.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Action Item:&lt;/strong> A poll will be posted in the Elements Chat to gauge interest and support for this idea.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Other Topics:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Postponed Items:&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Discussion on software funding opportunities and the open-access collection has been deferred to the next meeting. Please contribute ideas and materials in the meantime.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CRAN and OpenArcheo Discussion:&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A suggestion emerged during a discussion about CRAN&amp;rsquo;s role. It was proposed that OpenArcheo could benefit from a filter for package language, making it easier to identify R packages not hosted on CRAN, particularly if issues persist with the CRAN Task View for Archaeology.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-november-6-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, November 6, 2024&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>40th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-09-04/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-09-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>11 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="invited-talk">Invited talk&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Nicolas Frerebeau introduced the tesselle R package suite, an integrated set of packages for various archaeological research applications: &lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some of the questions that were raised in the discussion:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>How to measure the impact of an R package?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Nicolas has published multiple papers on individual tesselle packages (e.g. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01821">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01821&lt;/a>) and he can observe the number of citations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He recommends adding a CITATION.cff file to each repository: &lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/managing-your-repositorys-settings-and-features/customizing-your-repository/about-citation-files">https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/managing-your-repositorys-settings-and-features/customizing-your-repository/about-citation-files&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist suggested to use the GitHub search to find R code loading a given package: &lt;a href="https://github.com/search?q=library%28kairos%29&amp;amp;type=code">https://github.com/search?q=library%28kairos%29&amp;amp;type=code&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How to apply for funding for scientific software projects?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We decided to compile some resources about this question, first in a discussion thread on GitHub, later potentially on the SSLArch website: &lt;a href="https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52">https://github.com/orgs/sslarch/discussions/52&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is it better to split a set of entangled R packages (or generally libraries/modules for any programming language) over many repos, or keep them together in a large monorepo?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This has been extensively discussed by software developers. Both approaches come with their own advantages and disadvantages.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which licences should be used for archaeological research software?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://choosealicense.com">https://choosealicense.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Restrictive licenses may discourage adoption in the commercial archaeology sector.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Funding institutions may consider software licensing more explicitly in the future (see UK).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-ssla-projects">SIG-SSLA Projects&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Project: Reviving the &amp;ldquo;Tools for quantitative analysis&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We decided to adopt the GitHub discussion forum for some general exchange: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar/discussions">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar/discussions&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Project: Session for CAA2025
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz and Clemens Schmid have started to work on an abstract about programming interfaces (APIs, CLIs, DSLs - Domain specific languages) in archaeology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The google docs link was shared in the matrix chat, interested group members are invited to join the session organisation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-october-2-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, October 2, 2024&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>Applying Archaeological Research Software Engineering as Little Minions: Statistical &amp; Computational Approaches to Daily Archaeological Tasks</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/eaa2024_session/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/eaa2024_session/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When&lt;/strong>: 2024-08-31
&lt;strong>Where&lt;/strong>: Sapienza University of Rome
Piazzale Aldo Moro, 5, 00185 Roma RM, Italy&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Nowadays computer applications as well as statistical and computational approaches constitute a big part of the toolbox of every archaeologist, as they open tremendous possibilities for all research. These can be ready-to-use (proprietary) software applications but also “Little Minions” (self-scripted tools) or research software (e.g. implementation of statistic algorithms in R, Python), which are written by researchers. Both, research software and research data are part of Computational Archaeology and play an important role in up-to-date archaeological research. Optimally research data (and software) is FAIR(4RS) – Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Re-usable (for Research Software) – and reproducible of which other users can benefit from or even develop further. The increasing number of topics and papers at the international and national chapters of the CAA show manifold applications but also implications. Working Groups like the SIG SSLA (&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io">https://sslarch.github.io&lt;/a>) or the “Little Minions” (&lt;a href="https://littleminions.link">https://littleminions.link&lt;/a>) also deal with Computational Archaeology and are building a community.
Several initiatives, such as the German National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI) – especially NFDI4Objects – or the European Open Science Cloud (EOSC), engage with this topic to strengthen the position of Computational Archaeologists and Research Software Engineers, highlight the scientific merit of their work, and ensure researchers receive credit for computational approaches, software development, as well as for writing papers.
To support this, this session invites contributions dealing with various aspects of Computational Archaeology, but not limited to:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>39th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-05-08/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-05-08/</guid><description>&lt;p>6 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-and-announcements">Open exchange and announcements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Even more summerschools:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>atRium Brno Training School on computational archaeology
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://petrpajdla.github.io/atRium">https://petrpajdla.github.io/atRium&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>funding available for participants
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>planned for 16-20 September 2024, deadline for applications is May 31st&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Summer School in Digital Palaeography
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.uni-goettingen.de/en/digital+palaeography+summer+school+2024/684265.html">https://www.uni-goettingen.de/en/digital+palaeography+summer+school+2024/684265.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Neural Networks for Archaeologists, with Python
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://www.mappaproject.org/nn4archaeologists">http://www.mappaproject.org/nn4archaeologists&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EUROPEAN DS4CH: European Data Space for Cultural Heritage
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Flagship initiative of the European Commission to accelerate the digital transformation of Europe’s cultural sector, and foster the creation and reuse of content in the cultural and creative sectors&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.photoconsortium.net/european-ds4ch">https://www.photoconsortium.net/european-ds4ch&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>GitHub &amp;amp; ORCID collaboration
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://info.orcid.org/orcid-and-github-sign-memorandum-of-understanding">https://info.orcid.org/orcid-and-github-sign-memorandum-of-understanding&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>it is now possible to link GitHub and ORCID accounts&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New software tool for PCA analysis in genetics (triggered a discussion in the group about the use of PCA in archaeogenetics)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-024-05770-1">https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-024-05770-1&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>R packages to make PCA and other methods of multivariate statistics available within tidy(verse) workflows
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/corybrunson/ordr">https://github.com/corybrunson/ordr&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/ISAAKiel/quantAAR">https://github.com/ISAAKiel/quantAAR&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Online Survey of Cultural Heritage Professionals
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://alexandriaarchive.org/fair-care/">https://alexandriaarchive.org/fair-care/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>TETRARCHs: Running seminar series on computational archaeology
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.tetrarchs.org/index.php/category/seminars">https://www.tetrarchs.org/index.php/category/seminars&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Archaeological paper in Nature by Riris et al.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Frequent disturbances enhanced the resilience of past human populations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07354-8">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07354-8&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="project-discussion">Project discussion&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Context: Reviving old archaeological research software tools&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Concrete project: Reviving the &amp;ldquo;Tools for quantitative analysis&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="http://tfqa.com">http://tfqa.com&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>James Allison contacted the author Keith Kintigh:&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Prof. Kintigh appreciates the effort of rewriting some of the tools in R; he would even be willing to get involved directly&lt;/li>
&lt;li>TFQA was a commercial project, but there is no significant demand for the old distribution, so making the rewritten code/tools openly available is OK&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some tools are computationally intensive and optimization may be an issue in R&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are some potential numerical analysis issues in computing the factorials for binomial probabilities for some of the tools - developers should rely on established numerical libraries and not implement this math from scratch&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Matt Peeples has already implemented some of the tools in R (&lt;a href="https://mattpeeples.net/data-and-software)">https://mattpeeples.net/data-and-software)&lt;/a>, but his focus was on the core algorithms - wrapping them in a convenient, well documented functions is still an open task&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Various TFQA tools are described across different publications. See the discussion in the Google group for some relevant papers
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/8na4TLw47Xg">https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/8na4TLw47Xg&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Potential targets/low-hanging fruits to work on:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>An R package compiling different archaeological diversity measure algorithms&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A package or a set of blogposts/scripts reproducing some of the spatial data analysis tools&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A key feature of TFQA is domain-appropriate resampling (e.g. temporal or spatial resampling), which should be preserved in any rewritten version&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Technical observations about TFQA:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Multiple of the open-source TFQA tools are written in Delphi, a dialect of Pascal (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delphi_(software)">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delphi_(software)&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They were usually compiled for MS-DOS or MS-Windows, some compiled executables do not run any more on modern Windows versions and require emulation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The tools typically have a simple TUI (terminal user interface) that guides the user through the input preparation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some of the tools are pretty complex and include multiple subcommands&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Further discussion should happen on GitHub in dedicated issues at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-june-5-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, June 5, 2024&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We invited Nicolas Frerebeau to introduce the tesselle R package collection: &lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>38th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-04-03/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-04-03/</guid><description>&lt;p>8 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-and-announcements">Open exchange and announcements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New version of &amp;ldquo;OmnesViae&amp;rdquo;, a route planner for the Roman Empire: &lt;a href="https://omnesviae.org">https://omnesviae.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>WebAssembly for scientific computing is gaining momentum: &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00725-1">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00725-1&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New R package &amp;ldquo;centerline&amp;rdquo; to retrieve the centerline of spatial polygons (useful for spatial analysis/map plotting): &lt;a href="https://github.com/atsyplenkov/centerline">https://github.com/atsyplenkov/centerline&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New online platform &amp;ldquo;Digital Atlas of Ancient Arabia&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href="https://ancientarabia.huma-num.fr/atlas">https://ancientarabia.huma-num.fr/atlas&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conference on distributed data management: &lt;a href="https://distribits.live">https://distribits.live&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New Radon Database announced (not online yet) which will combine radon and radon-b: &lt;a href="https://radon.ufg.uni-kiel.de">https://radon.ufg.uni-kiel.de&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://radon-b.ufg.uni-kiel.de">https://radon-b.ufg.uni-kiel.de&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Mosaic Summer School 2024 (Kiel, Germany) about chronological data analysis was officially announced now: &lt;a href="https://lscholtus.gitlab.io/mosaicchrono">https://lscholtus.gitlab.io/mosaicchrono&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Another summer school titled &amp;ldquo;Computer and Geoscience in Archaeology&amp;rdquo; (Dresden, Germany) is open for applications: &lt;a href="https://www.htw-dresden.de/hochschule/fakultaeten/info-math/studium/studiengang-archaeoinformatik/summer-school-computer-science-in-archaeology">https://www.htw-dresden.de/hochschule/fakultaeten/info-math/studium/studiengang-archaeoinformatik/summer-school-computer-science-in-archaeology&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And one more summer school, the &amp;ldquo;Venice Summer School in Digital and Public Humanities&amp;rdquo; (Venice, Italy), as well: &lt;a href="https://www.unive.it/pag/39288">https://www.unive.it/pag/39288&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="project-discussion">Project discussion&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New SIG SSLA group project about reviving old, archaeological research software
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pitches:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Lisa Steinmann: Bringing the Quantatools R Package to CRAN
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Code: &lt;a href="https://github.com/maciejkasinski/quantatools">https://github.com/maciejkasinski/quantatools&lt;/a> and now &lt;a href="https://github.com/lsteinmann/quantatools">https://github.com/lsteinmann/quantatools&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Context: &lt;a href="https://publikationen.uni-tuebingen.de/xmlui/bitstream/handle/10900/101850/CAA2017_Kubicka-Kasinski_The%20Metrological%20Research_OA.pdf">https://publikationen.uni-tuebingen.de/xmlui/bitstream/handle/10900/101850/CAA2017_Kubicka-Kasinski_The%20Metrological%20Research_OA.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>State: The author, Maciej Kasiński, is not maintaining the project any more and is fine with a fork&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison: Recovering some core functionality from WinBasp
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Context: &lt;a href="https://baspsoftware.org">https://baspsoftware.org&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/WinBASP">https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/WinBASP&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>State: The author, Irwin Scollar, is not working on the software any more&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz and Christoph Rinne obtained a copy of the code (16-bit Fortran) at some point in the past&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some functionality is already replaced by other tools, e.g. &amp;ldquo;tosca&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://martinhinz.shinyapps.io/tosca">https://martinhinz.shinyapps.io/tosca&lt;/a>) for Seriation/Correspondence Analysis or postaar (&lt;a href="https://github.com/ISAAKiel/postAAR-python">https://github.com/ISAAKiel/postAAR-python&lt;/a>) for the detection of structures in posthole fields&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison: Tools for quantitative Analysis
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Context: &lt;a href="http://tfqa.com">http://tfqa.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>State: The author, Keith Kintigh, may still be working on it. The software has been commercially distributed in the past&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe has started to compile a list of alternative solutions for the individual tools: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Matt Peeples has implemented some alternatives: &lt;a href="https://mattpeeples.net/data-and-software">https://mattpeeples.net/data-and-software&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz: CoinCalc
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Code: &lt;a href="https://github.com/JonatanSiegmund/CoinCalc">https://github.com/JonatanSiegmund/CoinCalc&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Context: &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0305440317301309">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0305440317301309&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some of the functionality was already been implemented in another package &amp;ldquo;tapas&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href="https://github.com/JonatanSiegmund/CoinCalc/issues/2">https://github.com/JonatanSiegmund/CoinCalc/issues/2&lt;/a>, so &lt;a href="https://github.com/wfinsinger/tapas">https://github.com/wfinsinger/tapas&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>See the SIG SSLA chat at &lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a> to see how these ideas are further discussed and developed&lt;/li>
&lt;li>General questions raised in the discussion:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Is it good to provide simple graphical user interfaces, when we as a SIG actually want to encourage the use of scripting languages to ensure computational reproducibilty?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Did some of these old tools produce (proprietary?) data formats and would it be valuable to implement conversion tools to transform this data to more modern, open and human- and machine-readable formats?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-may-8-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, May 8, 2024&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We invited Nicolas Frerebeau to introduce the tesselle R package collection: &lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>37th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-03-06/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-03-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl were present&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open Exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>John Aycock will give a talk on tuesday on archaeogaming: &lt;a href="https://www.sas.ac.uk/events/archaeogaming-antics-computer-science-meets-archaeology">https://www.sas.ac.uk/events/archaeogaming-antics-computer-science-meets-archaeology&lt;/a>, London time zone 4-5pm&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New ggplot2 release 3.5.0: &lt;a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2024/02/ggplot2-3-5-0/">https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2024/02/ggplot2-3-5-0/&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>changes implementation of legends and may break code&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Job postings for ADS positions: &lt;a href="https://archaeo.social/@BlckheathHopper/112004422203426152">https://archaeo.social/@BlckheathHopper/112004422203426152&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clarivate&amp;rsquo;s Web of Science and JOSS (Journal of Open Source Software, minimal review process on Github, 2-page introductions to software, nice to have something to cite) - dispute: &lt;a href="https://neuromatch.social/@jonny/112012152112087956">https://neuromatch.social/@jonny/112012152112087956&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Short update on French CAA chapter: sounds good, says Julian Laabs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>MOSAIC summer school 2024: no news yet?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison on EAA chapter of SIG interest: 9 papers submitted, 8 accepted
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The organizers have not yet decided whether there will be an open space for spontanously presenting during the session (similar to the Little Minion sessions at CAA)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>At EAA everyone may only present one main-author presentation, so these short elevator pitches might be great as a second minor presentation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="survey-on-sig-presentations-and-projects">Survey on SIG presentations and projects&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We will ask Nicolas Frerebreau first, then Shawn Graham, Jörg Baten and Daniel Kondor&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We will aks Nicolas to join us for the May meeting and see how it goes from there&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Winner for SIG project: Make old software useful again
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>e.g. &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison has some old software in Turbo Pascal (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turbo_Pascal">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turbo_Pascal&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There might be automatic code translation programs already implemented, depends on the pascal version&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maybe LLMs could be useful, but buggy - sometimes helpful, sometimes take longer than to do it by hand&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How do we get more concrete with this idea?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Gather project ideas and use a meeting to pitch them, then decide together which ones might be interesting for enough for ppl to create a working group&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The result does not need to be an R package&lt;/li>
&lt;li>@Everyone: please look for fitting little programs we could work on&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="map-of-computational-archaeology-teaching-material">Map of Computational Archaeology Teaching Material&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The map could be a bit more interesting, so more worthwhile to re-visit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ideas to achieve that:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Automatically query papers for key words relating to the topics on the map?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ben Marwick&amp;rsquo;s automated R Archaeology paper bot did something similar? -&amp;gt; Is he still maintaing that? &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology/blob/master/README.md#publications-that-include-r-code">https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology/blob/master/README.md#publications-that-include-r-code&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Highlight some specific, particularly good materials? Could help ppl to choose where to start?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Re-toot the map regularly to remind ppl and invite them to add material
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Easy to do this automatically every time the map is updated for mastodon -&amp;gt; but this depends on ppl adding new material in the first place&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-3rd-april-2024">next meeting: 3rd April 2024&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>36th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-02-07/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2024-02-07/</guid><description>&lt;p>13 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A number of new people attended the meeting: Mathias Bellat, Lisa Steinmann, Julian Laabs, Andrea Titolo&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Various colleagues from France are in the process of creating a national CAA chapter&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Oliver Nakoinz announced that there will be a Mosaic summer school in Kiel 2024. Topic: Handling chronological data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist and Joe Roe shared a preprint about &amp;ldquo;Collaborative practices in an emerging community of archaeological software engineers&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href="http://zackbatist.info/openarchaeo-collaboration">http://zackbatist.info/openarchaeo-collaboration&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist applied some major changes to OpenArchaeo and documented them in a blog post: &lt;a href="https://blog.zackbatist.info/2024/02/02/pruning-open-archaeo">https://blog.zackbatist.info/2024/02/02/pruning-open-archaeo&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mathias Bellat asked the SSLA community for feedback on a data analysis script: &lt;a href="https://github.com/Mathias75018/ML_article">https://github.com/Mathias75018/ML_article&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Allison reminded us of the SSLA-co-organized EAA session &amp;ldquo;Applying Archaeological Research Software Engineering as Little Minions: Statistical &amp;amp; Computational Approaches to Daily Archaeological Tasks&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/eaa2024_session">https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/eaa2024_session&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt made us aware of &amp;ldquo;tesselle&amp;rdquo;, a collection of R packages for research and teaching in archaeology: &lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Thomas Huet has announced his plan to develop a project based on Python and Jupyter for Google Earth Engine (GEE), using the &lt;code>ee&lt;/code> library, to manage satellite imagery along with the extensive heritage places from the &lt;a href="https://eamena.org/database">EAMENA database&lt;/a>. The goal of this project is to train a Machine Learning model. He encourages community members interested in this initiative to contact him.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="organisation">Organisation&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG slack channel will be deleted next week on Monday, 12th of February. The new chat is at &lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a> with an invite-only room for the SIG-SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brainstorming for external speakers we want to invite this year:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Shawn Graham, LLM&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jörg Baten, Archaeological data in Economic history (e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01700-y">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01700-y&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Daniel Kondor, Population booms and busts (&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-35920-z">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-35920-z&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nikolas Frerebeau, tesselle R packages (&lt;a href="https://www.tesselle.org">https://www.tesselle.org&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Andrea Manica, pastclim R package (&lt;a href="https://github.com/EvolEcolGroup/pastclim">https://github.com/EvolEcolGroup/pastclim&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brainstorming for new group projects:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Guidelines for newcomers? / FAQ / Mini blog posts
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Inspiration: &lt;a href="https://jon-e.net/monsterdon">https://jon-e.net/monsterdon&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Webpage that collates mastodon posts with a certain hashtag?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Intro to computational archaeology textbook (e.g. &lt;a href="https://o-date.github.io/draft/book/">https://o-date.github.io/draft/book/&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A Playful coding introduction website for archaeologists (maybe using webR)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recover old archaeological software that is not maintained any more (e.g. &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://github.com/kacebe/AtlantGIS">https://github.com/kacebe/AtlantGIS&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Organize a winter school together&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-march-6-2024">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, March 6, 2024&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>35th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-12-06/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-12-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>12 ppl attending&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="conference">conference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>some of us participated in Jena Big Historical Data conference (&lt;a href="https://bhdc.earth/)">https://bhdc.earth/)&lt;/a>: it was good, main topic was the analysis of big data&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>ONLINE 11th-12th December: Barcelona workshop: Social modelling and simulations: &lt;a href="https://heuristica.participa.cloud/conferences/SMSBarcelona2023">https://heuristica.participa.cloud/conferences/SMSBarcelona2023&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>free&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>open online debate space for until 10th December, log in and give your opinion&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>ArchaeFOSS takes placec next week: &lt;a href="https://www.archeofoss.org/2023/">https://www.archeofoss.org/2023/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>panel by Joe Roe and Zack Baptist on Social Media and Fediverse in archaeology&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="various">various&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>new: topic of dark data: unused data in databases, usually 60% in a database&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>34th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-10-04/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-10-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ben Marwick:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Archaeology CRAN Task View
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CRAN has updated the way task views are maintained&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ben et al. prepared a draft for an Archaeology task view: &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology/blob/master/Archaeology.md">https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology/blob/master/Archaeology.md&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Everybody is invited to check it for completeness and suggest changes on GitHub&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Incentivizing archaeological journals to request/support/verify computational reproducibility
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ben reached out to the editors of various journals to argue for more data/code sharing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He suggested two concrete changes:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The journals should support Open Research Badges (e.g. &lt;a href="https://authorservices.wiley.com/open-research/open-recognition-and-reward/open-research-badges.html)">https://authorservices.wiley.com/open-research/open-recognition-and-reward/open-research-badges.html)&lt;/a>, which is a relatively easy thing for the journals to adopt&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A more work-intensive idea involves to specify the new role of a &amp;ldquo;Associate Editor of Reproducibility&amp;rdquo;. This role involves checking the computational reproducibility of papers, if the authors opt-in.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The editors were pretty receptive to these ideas so far - Ben has more meetings lined up&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New paper: &amp;ldquo;Women in the Lab, Men in the Field? Correlations between Gender and Research Topics at Three Major Archaeology Conferences&amp;rdquo;
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>DOI: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00934690.2023.2261083">https://doi.org/10.1080/00934690.2023.2261083&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Code: &lt;a href="https://github.com/yichun33/archyconfgender">https://github.com/yichun33/archyconfgender&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ben&amp;rsquo;s short introduction of the paper sparked a discussion about gender parity in our group. When we organize meetings we should be conscious about who we invite to maintain a balance - not just regarding gender, but also regarding other diversity parameters. We could consider formalizing this notion in our statutes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Florian Thiery (&lt;a href="https://fthiery.de/">https://fthiery.de/&lt;/a>) contacted the SIG SSLA to ask if any of our members would like to join him in chairing a session at the EAA2024. The session will frame/discuss research software as a special kind of research data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>John Aycock asked a modified version of the question that already came up in the 31st meeting (2023-07-05). Back then he asked about programming language features archaeologists may desire. Now he focused on tools to translate from one language to another (transpilation). Keywords of the discussion:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Simpler ways to express chronological models (e.g. oxcal)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Visual coding, e.g. &lt;a href="https://education.rstudio.com/blog/2019/10/my-javascript-internship-at-rstudio">https://education.rstudio.com/blog/2019/10/my-javascript-internship-at-rstudio&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Standardized data analysis pipelines for certain data categories: burial site data, compositional data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Managing site data is a major unsolved question of archaeology, despite many attempts&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Other news items, mostly compiled from Mastodon by Clemens Schmid, Sophie Schmidt and Ben Marwick:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Typewriter-styled maps in ggplot2: &lt;a href="https://nrennie.rbind.io/blog/creating-typewriter-maps-r">https://nrennie.rbind.io/blog/creating-typewriter-maps-r&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Interesting discussion &amp;ldquo;How to comment on dead systems in a review&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href="https://archaeo.social/@Drdonnayates/111147003931585716">https://archaeo.social/@Drdonnayates/111147003931585716&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New fuzzy-join package: &lt;a href="https://github.com/beniaminogreen/zoomerjoin">https://github.com/beniaminogreen/zoomerjoin&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist&amp;rsquo;s PhD thesis is online: &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/8373390">https://zenodo.org/record/8373390&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>webR and shiny become integrated - just as predicted: &lt;a href="https://www.infoworld.com/article/3707250/shiny-r-web-framework-arrives-in-wasm.html">https://www.infoworld.com/article/3707250/shiny-r-web-framework-arrives-in-wasm.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The ROAD database got published: &lt;a href="https://archaeo.social/@sommer@fosstodon.org/110820072946462861">https://archaeo.social/@sommer@fosstodon.org/110820072946462861&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Inequality joins are now easy to do in the dplyr R package: &lt;a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/joins.html#inequality-joins">https://r4ds.hadley.nz/joins.html#inequality-joins&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The ADS has prepared a new archaeological data management guide/checklist: &lt;a href="https://www.archaeologists.net/digdigital">https://www.archaeologists.net/digdigital&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences">Conferences&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are currently open calls for papers for the CAA2024 in Auckland (&lt;a href="https://2024.caaconference.org">https://2024.caaconference.org&lt;/a>, until 19th October) and the ArcheoFOSS 2023 in Turin (&lt;a href="https://www.archeofoss.org/2023">https://www.archeofoss.org/2023&lt;/a>, until 20th October).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>33rd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-09-06/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-09-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attending&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="open-exchange">open exchange&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="eaa">EAA&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>happened.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>very full conference, great fun for those attending&lt;/li>
&lt;li>two sessions interesting to computational archaeology, we would like to hear more about:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="archaeoriddle">archaeoriddle&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>we would like to invite Simon and Alfredo (Cambridge) to talk about it at CAA&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="code-sustainability-workshop">code sustainability workshop&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>by Dries Draems&lt;/li>
&lt;li>gave a shoutout to computational world map&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sadly he couldn&amp;rsquo;t talk, so hopefully he can tell us more next time&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="recursive-programming-in-r-and-infinite-sequences">recursive programming in R and infinite sequences&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Clemens recommends a blogpost: &lt;a href="https://jcarroll.com.au/2023/08/18/taking-from-infinite-sequences">https://jcarroll.com.au/2023/08/18/taking-from-infinite-sequences&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens example:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>using Haskell and repl as an interactive compiler&lt;/li>
&lt;li>you can ask for an infinite number and it just starts counting&lt;/li>
&lt;li>can be nice for indexing -&amp;gt; give a list concrete indices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we don&amp;rsquo;t have to count anymore, how many indices we need, we can just ask it to stop when our list is done being indexed&lt;/li>
&lt;li>manipulation of infinite lists can&amp;rsquo;t be done in every language -&amp;gt; but you can do that in Haskell by mapping for this infinite list ,
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>e.g. to get only a list of even numbers (by doubling all entries)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>and then you can just get the first ten entries and because Haskell is lazy it will then only calculate the first ten values&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>you can do the same in R via recursion (R doesn&amp;rsquo;t have infinitive data structures by default) and then measure how deep we are in the recursion to &amp;ldquo;stop&amp;rdquo; at a certain point (like take the ten first values)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>but be careful with sys.calls (if your environment is not clean, this will not get you the correct number, because you&amp;rsquo;ve already done a few sys calls)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>R is a lazy language which makes it in theory sometimes very efficient&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>comments:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>lazyness can be interesting by database queries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>it&amp;rsquo;s more a fun exercise to learn more about the quirks of a language ;-)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="ssla-matrix-channel-within-the-workspace-of-chatarchaeosocial-hosted-by-joe-roe">SSLA Matrix channel within the workspace of chat.archaeo.social hosted by Joe Roe&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>on chat.archaeo.social there are e.g. jobs-channel, resource-channel -&amp;gt; check out the links postet there, there is some activity&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>32nd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-08-02/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-08-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attending&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="communication">communication&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SIG SSLA Twitter / X has still a bit more interaction than mastodon, so we&amp;rsquo;ll keep it for a bit longer&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we are moving from Slack to Matrix: &lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social/#">https://chat.archaeo.social/#&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>discussion to maybe bridge to the Computational Archaeology Discord &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/Z9UXwjASM5">https://discord.gg/Z9UXwjASM5&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>the discord had been very active for some time, but is now a bit slow as well&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rchaeology group now has a channel on chat.archaeo.social as well&lt;/li>
&lt;li>at the moment, each &amp;ldquo;subgroup&amp;rdquo; has their own #general channel &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; maybe these could be joined?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="links-shared">Links shared&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>internet archive scholar: &lt;a href="https://scholar.archive.org/">https://scholar.archive.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="papers--books-shared">papers / books shared&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Hinsen, Konrad, The Nature of Computational Models, Computing in Science &amp;amp; Engineering 25, 1, 2023, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2023.3286250">https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2023.3286250&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Da Vela, Raffaella; Franceschini, Mariachiara; Mazzilli, Francesca, Networks as Resources for Ancient Communities, &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.15496/publikation-82292">http://dx.doi.org/10.15496/publikation-82292&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Leonelli, Sabina, What distinguishes data from models? Euro Jnl Phil Sci 9, 22 (2019). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13194-018-0246-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13194-018-0246-0&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="talk-by-matthew-peeples">Talk by Matthew Peeples&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>book: Tom Brughmans, Matthew A. Peeples, Network Science in Archaeology, Cambridge Manuals in Archaeology, 2023.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>31st regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-07-05/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-07-05/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Preprint &amp;ldquo;Debating AI in archaeology: applications, implications, and ethical considerations&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/r2j7h">https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/r2j7h&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Posit package manager as an alternative to the retired MRAN (R package time machine) (&lt;a href="https://posit.co/blog/migrating-from-mran-to-posit-package-manager">https://posit.co/blog/migrating-from-mran-to-posit-package-manager&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>John Aycock (&lt;a href="https://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~aycock">https://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~aycock&lt;/a>) asked about missing software tools/programming language features for archaeology; Keywords of the discussion:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>text based interfaces&lt;/li>
&lt;li>writing, reading and reviewing should be simple&lt;/li>
&lt;li>reproducibility (&lt;a href="https://www.acm.org/publications/policies/artifact-review-and-badging-current">https://www.acm.org/publications/policies/artifact-review-and-badging-current&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>syntactic support for roman numerals in Futhark (&lt;a href="https://futhark-lang.org/blog/2017-04-01-roman-numerals.html">https://futhark-lang.org/blog/2017-04-01-roman-numerals.html&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>open-archaeo&amp;rsquo;s ToDo list (&lt;a href="https://github.com/zackbatist/open-archaeo/blob/master/ToDo.md#tools-or-resources-in-demand">https://github.com/zackbatist/open-archaeo/blob/master/ToDo.md#tools-or-resources-in-demand&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences">Conferences&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA 2024 in Auckland (&lt;a href="https://2024.caaconference.org">https://2024.caaconference.org&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Call for papers deadline: 11 September 2023&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conference dates: 8-12 April 2024&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Most present SIG SSLA members do not consider to participate, because of the high travel costs involved&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ArchaeoFOSS 2023 in Turin (&lt;a href="https://www.archeofoss.org/2023">https://www.archeofoss.org/2023&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Call for panels deadline: 10 August 2023&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conference dates: 12-13 December 2023&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe considers it a direct replacement/competitor for the CAA conference&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He and Zack Batist will host a panel on communication tools&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Big Historical data conference in Jena (&lt;a href="https://bhdc.earth">https://bhdc.earth&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Call for papers deadline: 14 July 2023&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conference dates: 22-25 November 2023&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All conferences are already added to the SIG SSLA Google calendar&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter vs. Mastodon:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG has a Mastodon account now (&lt;a href="https://archaeo.social/@CAA_SSLA">https://archaeo.social/@CAA_SSLA&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We keep our Twitter account running, but focus on Mastodon&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slack vs. Matrix
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For our internal communication we will move from Slack to a Matrix server hosted by Joe Roe (&lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The details will be organised by the steering committee and Joe, but all interested SIG members should already create an account at chat.archaeo.social&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Donations for the operation of the Matrix and Mastodon servers are welcome (&lt;a href="https://opencollective.com/archaeosocial">https://opencollective.com/archaeosocial&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-august-2-2023">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, August 2, 2023&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Matt Peeples will join us to talk about &lt;strong>Network Science in Archaeology&lt;/strong> (&lt;a href="https://book.archnetworks.net">https://book.archnetworks.net&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>30th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-06-07/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-06-07/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Recommendations:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A new book on network analysis in archaeology: &lt;a href="https://book.archnetworks.net/">https://book.archnetworks.net/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A didactic blog post on LLMs: &lt;a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/">https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A new R package/framework to use R for web applications: &lt;a href="https://docs.r-wasm.org/webr">https://docs.r-wasm.org/webr&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A number of important, geospatial R packages will be removed from CRAN, which has important implications for long-term reproducibility: &lt;a href="https://r-spatial.org/r/2023/05/15/evolution4.html">https://r-spatial.org/r/2023/05/15/evolution4.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joe Roe and Sophie Schmidt still plan to give a workshop about &lt;a href="https://github.com/features/actions">GitHub Actions&lt;/a>, maybe in the context of the next CAA meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Multiple SIG members participate in the CAA&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Future conferences task force&amp;rdquo;, that was created to improve the annual meetings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe hosts an &lt;a href="https://element.io/">element&lt;/a> instance (&lt;a href="https://chat.archaeo.social">https://chat.archaeo.social&lt;/a>). He will create a workspace there for the SIG SSLA and we will migrate over from our Slack chat. Slack will be connected to this new environment through a bridge&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt will create a Mastodon account for the SIG to slowly retire our Twitter account&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-august-2-2023">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, August 2, 2023&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We will try to invite Matt Peeples to talk about &lt;strong>Network Science in Archaeology&lt;/strong> (see above)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>29th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-05-03/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-05-03/</guid><description>&lt;p>​​
11 ppl attended
​&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>​&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="show-casing-of-some-databases">show casing of some databases&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Robert shows the &amp;ldquo;Heurist&amp;rdquo; database by ian johnson database: archaeology, social science
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>is easy to upload data (even 3D data)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>heurist.huma.num.fr&lt;/li>
&lt;li>built in record sheets, map, etc, quite general purpose&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://heurist.huma-num.fr/heurist/startup/">https://heurist.huma-num.fr/heurist/startup/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>node-goat: graph database
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nodegoat.net">https://nodegoat.net&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>easy to use for network analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>arches database
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://eamena-project.github.io/eamena-arches-dev/talks/2023-gmpca/pres/#/arches-it-stack">https://eamena-project.github.io/eamena-arches-dev/talks/2023-gmpca/pres/#/arches-it-stack&lt;/a>
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="computational-environments">computational environments&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>recent article about computational environments &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-01469-0">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-01469-0&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>discusses the renv R package, Ben Marwick was interviewed briefly for it, along with many others
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="new-methods">new methods&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>most archaeological data is visual data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>triple IF to describe image (&lt;a href="https://iiif.io/">https://iiif.io/&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>JSON format&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3Dhop will develop sth similar for 3D
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="caa-wrap-up">CAA wrap up&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SIG SSLA had a good meeting in person&lt;/li>
&lt;li>SIG SSLA had a successful session&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CAA ethics officer is being needed!
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="very-high-caa-conference-fees">very high CAA conference fees&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA steering committee is aware it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>task force is being developed to discuss new ideas about that&lt;/li>
&lt;li>at the moment mostly men, middle-aged and from Europe&lt;/li>
&lt;li>call to diversify! if you are interested, please join&lt;/li>
&lt;li>discussion:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>needs to be more accessible&lt;/li>
&lt;li>needs more outreach, esp. to Asia and Africa&lt;/li>
&lt;li>more accessibility via hybrid&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;international&amp;rdquo; is in the name&lt;/li>
&lt;li>professional conference centers are the main trouble (high fees, equipment is expensive) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; go somewhere else, esp. universities&lt;/li>
&lt;li>in European context it&amp;rsquo;s unusual not to be at university, in other areas (North America) it is more usual to be at a conference center&lt;/li>
&lt;li>more open about the size of the bursary for students, so they can plan according&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jim and Martin may be part of the task force, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact them
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-ssla-computational-archaeology-map">SIG SSLA computational archaeology map&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/">https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>filtering and searching mechanism is more user-friendly now (tags are click-able), search more inclusive (across all fields)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>please: everyone add new entries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>will be tweeted about soon!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>map is written in Elm, may need some familiarity to get used to it, if you are interested to check it out
​&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="geometric-morphometrics">geometric morphometrics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>​&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reproducing, Reusing, and Revising Code and Data in Archaeology</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2023_session/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2023_session/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When&lt;/strong>: 2023-04-05,08:30-13:00 CEST&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where&lt;/strong>: Room E107, RAI Congress Center, Europaplein 24, 1078 GZ Amsterdam&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This session aims at evaluating how reproducible research in archaeology is actually faring. It has been argued that reproducible research techniques such as publishing and sharing code as well as data speed up scientific progress (Marwick 2017, Schmidt &amp;amp; Marwick 2020). With the FAIR movement and the rise of (Linked) Open Data approaches there seem to be more and more archaeological data sets available. Code used for archaeological analysis is also increasingly published online. There are a growing number of openly available code examples that have been used for articles (see for R &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology">https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology&lt;/a>, or for Netlogo &lt;a href="https://www.comses.net/codebases/?query=archaeology">https://www.comses.net/codebases/?query=archaeology&lt;/a> ). In some cases, this shared code may be adapted into “little helpers”, small modules of research software, aka Little Minions (Thiery et al. 2021), that can be reused and individually adapted. The community of Research Software Engineers (RSE), people who create software applications for research, is growing. For better dissemination of these programs, they created the FAIR4RS principles (Hong et al. 2022). RSEs are fighting for scientific recognition by e.g. implementing the CFF format to cite software (Anzt et al. 2020). But despite this general progress, published articles reusing or adapting open data or code are rare in archaeology. It is difficult to assess how often code and data are reused for research, but the rate of reuse appears to be low (Huggett 2018, Marwick and Birch 2018). Open data and code may be reused more often for teaching (Cook et al. 2018, Gartski 2022, Marwick et al. 2019), but it is not clear how often this happens. In this session we would like to ask the following questions&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>28th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-03-01/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-03-01/</guid><description>&lt;p>? ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>new paper by Clemens:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/nevrome/mobest.analysis.2022">https://github.com/nevrome/mobest.analysis.2022&lt;/a>: uses ancient genomic data to reconstruct where people may have come from&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens tried to make it reproducible, but that&amp;rsquo;s difficult with high computation set ups, some of the submission scripts will probably be re-written for other set ups&lt;/li>
&lt;li>is a meta analysis, therefore no problem with big data accessibility &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; only links to other data sets&lt;/li>
&lt;li>data is shared by a lab in Harvard, so hoping the data will be available for the foreseeable future (copying the data may be difficult for legal reasons)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maybe the data will be later made accessibly more openly (cooperation coming up)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>all analysis is written in R, some Haskell is for management of computational pipeline (Haskell shake, similar to R targets), and some more command line tools&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>changing APIs can be a problem for reproducibility&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Thomas Huet: tries to set up a Workflow with google maps and asks for recommendation
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>extract spatial data from remote sensing, to get a learning data set for machine learning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>R gee package or ee by Python?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Python is used by more people&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Python is especially useful for spatial analysis (most GIS is written in Python), R would work also, though&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pyhton environments is more hard to set up&lt;/li>
&lt;li>machine learning part is probably also written in Python so maybe better stay with one language&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>deep learning workshop at CAA is booked out&lt;/li>
&lt;li>there was an R-workshop in Pisa (Francesco Carrer and Joe Roe): good feedback, probably will take place next year again (this was the fourth time already)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>if you have students that need an R intro&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>archaeovis-package by Sebastien Plutniak: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sebastien-plutniak/archeoviz">https://github.com/sebastien-plutniak/archeoviz&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>mostly for x-y-z projection of data and showing the stratigraphical position of artefacts after excavation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>tries to make non-scripting people use shiny&lt;/li>
&lt;li>preprint is submitted: &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7674699">https://zenodo.org/record/7674699&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>is at PCI for review&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>more GUIs for R are being developed&lt;/li>
&lt;li>in Clemens part of the workshop in Australia: 20-25 ppl attending
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>quite interesting talks, quite theoretical in part, very diverse topics, but always linked to quantitative methods and R scripting in these domains&lt;/li>
&lt;li>but Clemens just saw a couple of talks&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>software reviews: &lt;a href="https://research-squirrel-engineers.github.io/Impuls_SoftwareRezensionen_DGUF/Draft_EN.html">https://research-squirrel-engineers.github.io/Impuls_SoftwareRezensionen_DGUF/Draft_EN.html&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;digital reviews&amp;rdquo; in archaeological advancements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PCI offers the possbility to review software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>peer reviewing software is something else as reviewing software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>archeoFOSS community: already engaged in this topic?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>should the SIG engage?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>if there would be a centralised platform to find other people&amp;rsquo;s experiences it would be sensible&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a list of recommendations / reviews might be already useful&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;lists&amp;rdquo; of software are already avaiable&lt;/li>
&lt;li>software is changing all the time: so reviewing would be one step, but it should be starting point of involvement, improvement &amp;ndash; make a open source collaboration&lt;/li>
&lt;li>if done correctly this could be a great way to improve software (otherwise it might be very annoying for the author to be criticesed and not helped to improve)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>another point might be: making a software more known (also positive for the author)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>review paper: a paper that says &amp;ldquo;if you want to do this kindof analysis, you have these options&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, like a survey&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="teaching-materials-current-state-of-affairs">teaching materials: current state of affairs&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/">https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>new: introductory information added&lt;/li>
&lt;li>looks great!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>feature to maybe add: click on the tag and filter for the tag&lt;/li>
&lt;li>put it on our homepage (link or embed?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>where on the website
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>under &amp;ldquo;research output&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>or rather on top as its own tab?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>maybe important links on a side board (but check mobile view: it will go down to the botton)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>let&amp;rsquo;s discuss this on the github: issues for the website (also, should you find a problem with the map)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>topic for next meeting: how to improve our website&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="petr-pajdla-on-quarto">Petr Pajdla on Quarto&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace Rmarkdown (development will be continued) and written text stays markdown&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rmd documents should work with Quarto&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quarto is a Command Line Interface, more generic than the R dependent Rmarkdown&lt;/li>
&lt;li>very well written introduction: quarto.org&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quarto is build on Pandoc (may be needed to be installed seperately, esp. pandoc-citeproc for citation)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quarto is now shipped with Rstudio (you may be able to use it out of the box)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>projects workflow:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>quarto documents (extension qmd)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>has a similar YAML-header, but can also be seperated as _quarto.yml
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>splitting one project into several documents easier than with bookdown&lt;/li>
&lt;li>integrates author, name, email, orcid: easier to include than with Rmarkdown&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>publishing:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>quarto pub hosts slides, etc whatever, every easy to use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>github pages easy to set up&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>figure captions: now not any more put next to the ```{r
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>this was a bit unwieldy in Rmarkdown if the labels and captions got very long&lt;/li>
&lt;li>in Quarto same information as a comment #| &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; better readable&lt;/li>
&lt;li>labels need to be fig.xxx for figures and for tables tab.yyy&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>very easy to have a qmd document to become a presentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>::::{.colums} creates a div environment for tables for html&lt;/li>
&lt;li>revealjs renders to html&lt;/li>
&lt;li>same code goes to same output in html, PDF and docx &amp;lt;- details needs to be checked for the future&lt;/li>
&lt;li>css might not be well translated into other outputs, basic text colours will be the same&lt;/li>
&lt;li>citations work the same as in Rmarkdown (put the bib file and csl in the YAML)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>works also in visual mode&lt;/li>
&lt;li>integrating ready made images works the same -&amp;gt; &lt;img src="path" alt="caption">{#label}
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>label: &amp;ldquo;#fig-xxx&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>reference:&amp;quot;@fig-xxx&amp;quot;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>check cross-references&lt;/li>
&lt;li>supports other languages?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Python, R, Julia are implemented - can be used in the same document&lt;/li>
&lt;li>can the community provide kernels to enlargen the pool of supported languages?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>knitr or jupyter can be chosen for rendering, thereby using jupyters kernels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>more languages are supposed to come, if sth is installed on you computer, it should be possible to use&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rshiny in Rmarkdown was a great interactive possibility in the documents
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>can be done in Quarto as well&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>example of Quarto used for a course website: &lt;a href="https://gia.joeroe.io/">https://gia.joeroe.io/&lt;/a> (source at &lt;a href="https://github.com/joeroe/gis_in_archaeology">https://github.com/joeroe/gis_in_archaeology&lt;/a>)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>worked really well&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Petrs Diss uses Quarto: &lt;a href="https://github.com/petrpajdla/dataInfrastructures">https://github.com/petrpajdla/dataInfrastructures&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="advertisement-by-francesco-carrer">Advertisement by Francesco Carrer&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>2 fully funded 1-year MRes (master of research) + 3-year PhD for UK students (or foreign students that obtained their degree in the UK) at Newcastle University.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>(1) Spatial Analysis in Archaeology: &amp;ldquo;Spatial Analysis and Modelling to Investigate the Historic Character of Landscapes&amp;rdquo; - supervisor Francesco Carrer, co-supervisor Sam Turner, industrial partner Historic England; knowledge of GIS essential, knowledge of R or Python desirable.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>(2) Mathematical Archaeology: &amp;ldquo;Spatiotemporal modelling of Alpine agricultural revolution&amp;rdquo; - supervisor: Andrew Baggaley (Maths), co-supervisor Francesco Carrer, industrial partner Dolomiti National Park; experience with techniques for finding both numerical and analytic solutions to differential equations essential, working knowledge of Python or Fortran.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For more information, get in touch (&lt;a href="mailto:francesco.carrer@newcastle.ac.uk">francesco.carrer@newcastle.ac.uk&lt;/a>) and check the website (&lt;a href="https://geospatialcdt.ac.uk/studentship-projects/">https://geospatialcdt.ac.uk/studentship-projects/&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-we-will-meet-at-the-caa-more-info-where-and-when-will-be-distributed-on-slack">next we will meet at the CAA, more info (where and when) will be distributed on &lt;strong>Slack&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>to be discussed:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mastodon and Matrix&lt;/li>
&lt;li>how to improve on our websit&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>May: talk on morphometrics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>June: Zach offers to introduce LaTeX&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>27th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-02-06/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-02-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange">Open exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s CRAN time machine MRAN is getting shutdown soon. See an extensive discussion of alternatives for reproducibility of R code here: &lt;a href="https://www.brodrigues.co/blog/2023-01-12-repro_r">https://www.brodrigues.co/blog/2023-01-12-repro_r&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A new release of our beloved dplyr R package for data manipulation introduces interesting new features: &lt;a href="https://github.com/tidyverse/dplyr/releases/tag/v1.1.0">https://github.com/tidyverse/dplyr/releases/tag/v1.1.0&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ARCAS Workshop: The Australasian Cluster for Archaeological Science is organizing a 3-day online workshop on fostering good statistical practice in archaeology this week: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ARCAS_news/status/1621729679483994113">https://twitter.com/ARCAS_news/status/1621729679483994113&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-administrative-matters">SIG Administrative matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We decided to move the regular meeting date from the first Monday every month to the first Wednesday. The meeting time stays at 17:00 CET&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We decided to move the &amp;ldquo;Open Exchange&amp;rdquo; section to the beginning of the meeting to have enough time to inform each other about ongoing developments in the computational archaeology world&lt;/li>
&lt;li>See the minutes from 2023-01-09 (&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-01-09">https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-01-09&lt;/a>) for the planned changes to the Presentation format of our regular meeting. For the first meeting with external speakers in May we would like to find experts to introduce current developments in Geometric morphometrics (GMM)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We remind the SIG members to add relevant conferences/meetings to the SIG&amp;rsquo;s Google calendar&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>DAB2023: &lt;a href="https://dab23.archaeological.science">https://dab23.archaeological.science&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG members who participated found the presentations relevant and engaging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open Source Software in archaeology seems to be on a good way&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz (one of the organizers) confirmed that the panelists want to prepare a collective article summarizing the event&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The free and open livestream of the event was highlighted as a very positive feature of the conference by all present SIG members&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CAA2023: &lt;a href="https://2023.caaconference.org">https://2023.caaconference.org&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>All present members find the costs for participation in the conference too high&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s also highly regrettable that hybrid participation in the conference is not possible&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe, who headed the planned SIG workshop on Git, GitHub and CI/CD decided not to participate in the conference because of the high costs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We therefore retract the workshop offer. We will try to offer it independently of the CAA conference at another date&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There will be no formal SIG meeting during the conference, but an informal get-together at one of the evenings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The SIG Session will go ahead as planned&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-sig-meeting-wednesday-march-1-2023">Next SIG Meeting: Wednesday, March 1, 2023&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Petr Pajdla will introduce the scientific and technical publishing system Quarto (&lt;a href="https://quarto.org">https://quarto.org&lt;/a>), which essentially replaces RMarkdown&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We will briefly talk about the teaching material list and its presentation at &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology">https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology&lt;/a> to identify remaing ToDos&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>26th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-01-09/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2023-01-09/</guid><description>&lt;p>3 ppl attended (Board Meeting)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="administrative-matters">Administrative matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter/Mastodon: A Mastodon account is preferable, if possible via &lt;a href="https://archaeo.social">https://archaeo.social&lt;/a>. In the future, both channels should be used in parallel for the moment. Ideally, a common interface should be found to avoid duplicating workflows. Automatisms should be considered and implemented, e.g. when a new protocol is published.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Matrix: If possible and provided, the internal communication channel should be moved from Slack to Matrix. The implementation of the move will be communicated on Slack and in the mailing list.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dates for monthly meeting: The day of the week and time should be adjusted to the new circumstances of the new semester. A corresponding survey will be sent out to the members via Doodle.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings with Presentations: In general, the format was found to be good. However, we want to increase the participation of the audience. Therefore, this format will now only be held 4 times a year. We will invite more topic-specifically and less according to the current publication situation. A topic for the next invitation would be Quarto. Suggestions for topics are gladly accepted!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meetings without Presentations: It was noted that there was not enough space for general exchange. We will try to give more opportunities here, and perhaps stimulate this with current papers. However, we also hope that the members will then support this exchange and enrich it with contributions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA Amsterdam: We are planning a Meet, Greet and Drink. Tuesday or Thursday. We will find out an appropriate location.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Software Reviews: This would be a possible SIG activity for this year. We will informally compile a list of software worthy of review and see if this is of interest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Teaching: Workshops and tutorials already held by the SIG at CAA meetings should continue to be used in the long term. Therefore, these should be made available to the general public in revised form as teaching material, e.g. as blogposts.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Questionnaire to the entire CAA: In order to better identify needs regarding scripting languages, we are striving to create a questionnaire in this regard and send it to all CAA members via the CAA channels. This would be a project for 3 meetings.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-february-6-2023">Next Meeting: Monday, February 6, 2023&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>25th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-12-12/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-12-12/</guid><description>&lt;p>6 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="election-of-board-members">Election of board members&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>existing board (Martin Hinz, Sophie Schmidt, Clemens Schmid) re-elected by 100% vote of all other participants&lt;/li>
&lt;li>election cycles are two years&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="teaching-materials-map">Teaching Materials Map&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Clemens presented state of the map: &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/">https://sslarch.github.io/MapofComputationalArchaeology/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>List of tutorials is filter-able (names, authors, tags, programming language), links to points on the Map&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>more information can be shown with a &amp;ldquo;pop up&amp;rdquo; modal&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>the modal doesn&amp;rsquo;t yet work well in the mobile version (scrolling doesn&amp;rsquo;t fixate on the pop up)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>24th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-11-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-11-07/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="talk-by-lucy-timbrell">Talk by Lucy Timbrell&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Timbrell, L., Grove, M., Manica, A. et al. A spatiotemporally explicit paleoenvironmental framework for the Middle Stone Age of eastern Africa. Sci Rep 12, 3689 (2022). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07742-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07742-y&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>explicit model for precipitation and temperature at Middle Stone Age sites during several interglacial phases&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>reconstructs changes in behaviour and use of ecotones&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>all code in R&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>data and code online at &lt;a href="https://osf.io/y98rq/">https://osf.io/y98rq/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>used data from: &lt;a href="https://osf.io/8n43x">https://osf.io/8n43x&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>go read it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>23rd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-10-12/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-10-12/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="administrative-matters">Administrative matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The slack chat software is not suitable for us any more, because it deletes messages after 90 days. Martin Hinz and Joe Roe will prepare an experimental setup with the matrix chat software, which we can explore and discuss in the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2023:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG session &lt;em>S15. Reproducing, Reusing, and Revising Code and Data in Archaeology&lt;/em> should be advertised a bit more in the following two weeks until the abstract submission deadline is reached&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt and Joe Roe will look into the possibility of handing in a workshop proposal - probably an updated rerun of one of the previous workshops&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material list: A number of ToDos are open and we distributed tasks to make progress&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-november-7-2022">Next meeting: Monday, November 7, 2022&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>22nd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-09-12/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-09-12/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="showtell">Show&amp;amp;Tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://wccarleton.me/">Christopher Carleton&lt;/a> talked about his work and workflow in and around computational archaeology. Christopher has published multiple highly relevant papers in this domain. Just to name a few:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Carleton, W. C. (2020). Evaluating Bayesian Radiocarbon‐dated Event Count (REC) models for the study of long‐term human and environmental processes. Journal of Quaternary Science &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.3256">https://doi.org/10.1002/jqs.3256&lt;/a>
Carleton W. C., Groucutt HS. (2020). Sum things are not what they seem: Problems with point-wise interpretations and quantitative analyses of proxies based on aggregated radiocarbon dates. The Holocene &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0959683620981700">https://doi.org/10.1177/0959683620981700&lt;/a>
Carleton, W. C. , J. Conolly, and G. Iannone (2012). A locally-adaptive model of archaeological potential (LAMAP) Journal of Archaeological Science 39(11), 3371-3385, 2012 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2012.05.022">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2012.05.022&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/wccarleton/lamap">https://github.com/wccarleton/lamap&lt;/a>
Carleton, W., McCauley, B., Costopoulos, A., &amp;amp; Collard, M. (2018). An evolutionary agent-based model contradicts Dunnell’s version of the waste hypothesis for cultural elaboration. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/2h36u">https://doi.org/10.31235/osf.io/2h36u&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://github.com/wccarleton/abm_waste">https://github.com/wccarleton/abm_waste&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Workflows and experiences on collaborative working and community building using digital tools</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2022_session/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2022_session/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://2022.caaconference.org/programme/">2022-08-11, 15:30-17:00 BST&lt;/a>&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Online and Room 11 Examination Schools, 75-81 The High Street, Oxford, OX1 4BG&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For a long time now, archaeological research has not been conducted by individual researchers who come up with brilliant theories in their study rooms and investigate them by themselves and on their own terms. It is a fact that no serious scientific research can be conducted without substantial and extensive collaboration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The internet facilitated a significant change in work processes, something we have been able to experience vividly in the last two years. Since it was intended from the start as a tool to enable scientific exchange, it is all the more astonishing that collaborative work via the internet did not develop further from back-and-forth emailing of text manuscripts for such a long time. By now there are a variety of different systems and solutions: communication via Slack or Signal, co-writing via Google Docs or Overleaf, data co-creation in online database systems, Open Science Framework or Wikidata, as well as code co-development via GitHub or GitLab.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to navigate the coding archaeology world: an introduction to scientific co-creation using Git and Github</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2022_workshop/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2022_workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> 2022-08-08, 15:30 - 17:00 BTS&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Online and in person, Lecture Theatre at the School of Archaeology (1 South Parks Road, Oxford, OX1 3TG)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The archaeological community is moving beyond the traditional modes of scientific communication, such as research papers, monographs and conference talks, and interacts online on a daily basis. Especially for archaeologists, who use and develop advanced, computational tools, a new kind of platform increasingly extends mailing lists and social media here, and has proven invaluable for collaborative work: Version control systems to develop, share and test manuscripts, figures and code.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>21st regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-07-04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-07-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>We had a busy and productive meeting today, where we explored how exactly the teaching material map can be set up on our website.
We made some good progress and now have a working prototype. Please see the respective repository on GitHub if you&amp;rsquo;re interested.
Let me know if you do not know where to look or if you do not have access.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>20th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-06-13/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-06-13/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="news">news:&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>new discord channel for computational archaeology: &lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/Z9UXwjASM5">https://discord.com/invite/Z9UXwjASM5&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="update-on-caa">update on CAA:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>we&amp;rsquo;ve got a (lightening talk) session #S15&lt;/li>
&lt;li>workshop on Git and Github has been submitted&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-meeting-germanynetherlands">chapter meeting Germany/Netherlands&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CfP until 1st of July&lt;/li>
&lt;li>takes place October 5th-6th&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="teaching-materials-list">teaching materials list&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="google-doc">google doc:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>finalise: tagging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>see whether the tutorials are complete with info so far&lt;/li>
&lt;li>add more edges to go on the map as routes&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="teaching-materials-map-httpsgithubcomsslarchmapofcomputationalarchaeology">teaching materials map (&lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/MapofComputationalArchaeology)">https://github.com/sslarch/MapofComputationalArchaeology)&lt;/a>:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>access needed via the github of SSLARCH&lt;/li>
&lt;li>can be exported as png tiles&lt;/li>
&lt;li>need to look whether the github server needs any infrastructure to properly work with leaflet to properly display the tiles&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="lists--group">lists- group&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>to dos in filling the data base:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zack: tools used, programming, short description, topic, open archeo tags&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie: Authors and year created, language&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>edges between cities:&lt;/li>
&lt;li>with direction from easier to more complicated
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>todo Jim: Netlogo learning paths&lt;/li>
&lt;li>todo Sophie: starts on R learning paths&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>would it be sensible to create a script that takes the tags according to the maps group to automatically place the &amp;ldquo;tutorial-cities&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="map-group">map group&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>there is a github repo which takes the maps and visualises them&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we can take this as a discussion basis for which to link and where to place tutorial-cities&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>19th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-05-02/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-05-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2022:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Our SIG SSLA session has 5(+3?) submissions, which are now all in review.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is still no way to submit workshops and we therefore still haven&amp;rsquo;t submitted ours.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material list:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt and others started to work on a unified tagging vocabulary for the available list.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens Schmid and Robert Bischoff came up with a creative solution to visualize the material in a fun and engaging way (Details omitted from the minutes).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Help is needed for all of these efforts: Check out the #teaching-materials channel on slack.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Open Digital Archaeology Textbook (Shawn Graham et al.):
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Shawn Graham is open to hand the lead for a second edition over to another author/editor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Volunteers can contact Zack Batist.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="showtell">Show&amp;amp;Tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mikel Díaz-Rodríguez presented on the analysis in his paper &lt;em>Evaluating the effectiveness of three spatial cluster analysis methods on
Palaeolithic site location distributions in Galicia, NW Iberian Peninsula&lt;/em> (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2021.103323">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jasrep.2021.103323&lt;/a>) and shared some of his experiences in making it reasonably reproducible.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-june-13-2022">Next meeting: Monday, June 13, 2022&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>18th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-04-04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-04-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="agenda">Agenda&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>further develop the SIG SSLA teaching materials list: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1oiOaKQu5sqj0IV99PY7Qr1FpvQ0QaEqH1pMKK9uDALw/edit#gid=0">https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1oiOaKQu5sqj0IV99PY7Qr1FpvQ0QaEqH1pMKK9uDALw/edit#gid=0&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="short-intro-of-rchaeologists-resources-by-bjorn">short intro of rchaeologists resources by Bjorn&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>kept simple to not overwhelm beginners&lt;/li>
&lt;li>will add resources to archaeology chapter&lt;/li>
&lt;li>very focused&lt;/li>
&lt;li>simple md page&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="discussion-about-teaching-materials-list">discussion about teaching materials list&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>include simple non-archaeology specific introductions to&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>that keep being updated&lt;/li>
&lt;li>e.g. data carpentries material&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>topics&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>R&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Python&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bash&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Git&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Netlogo&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>idea: create an opinionated graph, in a way a decision tree&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>17th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-03-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-03-07/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Discussion on structure and content of the regular SIG-SSLA meetings
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ideas in the conversation
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The current monday date is an issue for some people, but there is no obvious need for another meeting time survey&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The SIG-SSLA meeting will most likely always stay a rather small event, due to the limited total size of the computational archaeology community
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The group&amp;rsquo;s practical activitis should be more of a focus: e.g. Martin Hinz&amp;rsquo;s text book project or the teaching material list&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Show&amp;amp;Tell presentations are a clear pull-factor, that should be emphasized&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Concrete decisions
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We want to put more focus on the Show&amp;amp;Tell section:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>They will be repositioned to happen at the beginning of the meetings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We will explicitly invite authors of (recently) published papers to present their work (Ben Marwick&amp;rsquo;s CTV has a section with &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology#publications-that-include-r-code">relevant papers&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The presentations should still be small, informal lightning talks with a focus on hands-on exploration of the code in a given paper&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We want to experiment with an alternating structure, where we switch between more Show&amp;amp;Tell-focused and more project work-focused meetings&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2022: Deadline for the CfP is March 21st. Everybody is invited to join the SIG-SSLA workshop or submit a paper to the related session&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ArchaeoFOSS2022: The Call for Panels &lt;a href="https://www.archeofoss.org/2022/call-for-panels">is open&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Klassifikator project (Sophie Schmidt, Martin Hinz, et al.)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material for classification methods in archaeology: &lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/oliver.nakoinz/klassifikator">https://gitlab.com/oliver.nakoinz/klassifikator&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="showtell">Show&amp;amp;Tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Linked open pipes (Florian Thiery)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Define and describe workflows and pipelines in and outside the Linked Open Data community: &lt;a href="http://linkedpipes.xyz">http://linkedpipes.xyz&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The slides for this presentation are available &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1NSrEXxjLyJAA5IWU4KHHBn_g7geDbg49CinAZy_km6g">here&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-april-4-2022">Next meeting: Monday, April 4, 2022&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the next meeting we will work together on the curated teaching material list. Please check the relevant slack channel before the meeting&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>16th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-02-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-02-07/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>EAA2022: There are a number of sessions relevant for computational archaeologists. The SIG-SSLA twitter team has compiled &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CAA_SSLA/status/1490742129081131016">a thread&lt;/a> listing some of them&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CAA2022: The CfP will open during the week commencing 14th February 2022 and end on March 21st. Consider to join the SIG-SSLA workshop or submit a paper to the related session&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ben Marwick Cran Task View proposal
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Due to a recent change in the way &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/">CTVs&lt;/a> are submitted, it may be possible now to create one dedicated to archaeology&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ben Marwick has prepared a proposal &lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology/blob/master/Archaeology.md">here&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This does not interfere with &lt;a href="https://open-archaeo.info/">open-archaeo&lt;/a>, which serves as a software database, whereas the CTV would be an R-specific guide or entry point&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One issue of the current proposal is, that many archaeology-related R packages are not on CRAN&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contributions are welcome&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-march-7-2022">Next meeting: Monday, March 7, 2022&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Show&amp;amp;Tell by Florian Thiery proposed for this meeting had to be moved to the the next one in March&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>15th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-01-10/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2022-01-10/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We moved to the VoIP software zoom for our meetings after various technical difficulties with jitsi in the last meeting. Internet connection issues in this meeting again caused problems, though.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>International Mountain Conference 2022 (11.09. to 15.09.): Francesco Carrer hosts the session &lt;a href="https://www.imc2022.info/portfolio/id20-geospatial-technologies-in-mountain-archaeology">ID20: Geospatial technologies in mountain archaeology&lt;/a> and invited us to submit papers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CAA2022 (09.08. - 11.08.): We discussed if and how the SIG should participate and came up with two events, which should generally cover the topics collaborative working, community building, commons &amp;amp; codes of conduct within the archaeological, scientific community and how modern, digital tools can help. As the Call for Sessions closes on the 17th, we will have to hurry with our abstracts.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A workshop could provide a practical introduction to Git, GitHub and other related tools. Sophie Schmidt and Clemens Schmid want to prepare that &amp;ndash; others are very welcome to join (Petr?).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A session with lightning talks and group discussion could collect and discuss options and challenges in that domain. Martin Hinz and Florian Thiery will spearhead that. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested to join, please take a look into the new Slack channel #caa2022session.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="show-and-tell">Show and tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Francesco Carrer presented the idea and the code for his paper: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2020.105306">The application of Local Indicators for Categorical Data (LICD) to explore spatial dependence in archaeological spaces&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The code for the paper is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/rsbivand/LICD_article">here&lt;/a>, including a reference implementation of the core algorithm.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This code went through professional &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4279275">code review/replication&lt;/a> by the CODECHECK initiative. This could be an interesting option for many of us.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-february-7-2022">Next meeting: Monday, February 7, 2022&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>14th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-12-06/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-12-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>10 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>the next meeting will take place on the &lt;strong>10th January&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Francesco Carrer will give a short intro on the tools for spatial statistics he&amp;rsquo;s been developing&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2022: The conference will probably take place in July (announcement via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CAA_Int/status/1464584391003418626?s=20">twitter&lt;/a> ), but no exact dates have been released yet&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material list: Sophie Schmidt has shared a google document in the respective slack channel. Please invest some minutes of brainstorming to add the relevant materials you know.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="discussion">Discussion&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>interesting blogs
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="latex-ninja.com/">LaTeX Ninja&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2020-12-new-year-new-blogdown/">Alison Hill on using blogdown&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/atom-for-scholarly-writing-with-markdown">Ben Marwick on using Atom&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="show-and-tell">Show and tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Show and tell focused on pipeline tools&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>13th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-11-01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-11-01/</guid><description>&lt;p>8 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The twitter team asks for input. Please see the etherpad document here: &lt;a href="https://etherpad.wikimedia.org/p/ssla-tweets">https://etherpad.wikimedia.org/p/ssla-tweets&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reminder that we have a Google calendar and everyody is invited to add relevant events in and around computational archaeology: &lt;a href="https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=uitkaq4o6b90gbcca2bh1qqa3g%40group.calendar.google.com">https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=uitkaq4o6b90gbcca2bh1qqa3g%40group.calendar.google.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2022: To our knowledge the conference date is still unknown&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Georg Roth forwarded an invitation to a math lecture related to geometric morphometrics: &lt;a href="https://www.math-berlin.de/academics/bms-fridays">https://www.math-berlin.de/academics/bms-fridays&lt;/a>. The relevant working group has a website here: &lt;a href="https://morphomatics.github.io">https://morphomatics.github.io&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>As part of the current Thematic Einstein Semester on “Mathematics of Imaging in Real-Word Challenges“,
a series of tandem tutorials will be held throughout the winter semester 2021/22.

These tutorials will take place as online lectures from 2 to 4 pm (Berlin time) on:

- Friday, 29 October 2021: &amp;#34;Classical vs. Data Driven Regularization Methods in Imaging&amp;#34;
- **Friday, 26 November 2021: &amp;#34;Population wide Medical Image and Shape Analysis&amp;#34;**
- Friday, 18 February 2022: &amp;#34;Neural MRI&amp;#34;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material list: Sophie Schmidt has shared a google document in the respective slack channel. Please invest some minutes of brainstorming to add the relevant materials you know.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="show-and-tell">Show and tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>James Allison presented R code to parse, transform and analyse the output of the Agent-based &amp;ldquo;Village model&amp;rdquo; software: &lt;a href="https://github.com/jallison7/village-output-analysis">https://github.com/jallison7/village-output-analysis&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Some relevant feedback items:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Plotly might simplify interactive data analysis (&lt;a href="https://plotly.com/r/">https://plotly.com/r/&lt;/a>, &lt;code>ggplotly()&lt;/code>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stream processing might be useful to summarise large text files that do not fit into memory (e.g. &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/nevrome/2d13733583d9f0c0dfaadc4c0b12aedf">https://gist.github.com/nevrome/2d13733583d9f0c0dfaadc4c0b12aedf&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Split-Apply-Combine&amp;rdquo; workflows can be implemented nicely with dplyr&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code>group_by&lt;/code> + &lt;code>summarize&lt;/code> (e.g. &lt;a href="https://datacarpentry.org/R-genomics/04-dplyr.html#split-apply-combine_data_analysis_and_the_summarize()_function">https://datacarpentry.org/R-genomics/04-dplyr.html#split-apply-combine_data_analysis_and_the_summarize()_function&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>High performance computing environments for model runs can also be rented, if no such infrastructure is available (e.g. &lt;a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/how-to-run-rstudio-on-aws-in-under-3-minutes-for-free-65f8d0b6ccda">https://towardsdatascience.com/how-to-run-rstudio-on-aws-in-under-3-minutes-for-free-65f8d0b6ccda&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-monday-december-6-2021">Next meeting: Monday, December 6, 2021&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>12th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-10-04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-10-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>6 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Following a doodle poll we decided to try another regular meeting date for the following months: The first monday every month, 17pm, CEST. Please see the google calendar for more information.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In October 2021:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New Approaches in Digital Archaeology: &lt;a href="https://archaeology.nsc.ru/events/nada">https://archaeology.nsc.ru/events/nada&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Theoretical Approaches to Computational Archaeology: &lt;a href="http://www.prehistoire.org/offres/gestion/actus_515_42365-911/theoretical-approaches-to-computational-archaeology.html">http://www.prehistoire.org/offres/gestion/actus_515_42365-911/theoretical-approaches-to-computational-archaeology.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Please remeber to add these and other new events to the SIG&amp;rsquo;s Google calendar.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Teaching material list
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt will now create a Google sheet document to collect information&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ideally every SIG member should invest 10 minutes of brainstorming to collect teaching resources&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The list will then be sorted by the core members of the teaching list committee&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="show-and-tell">Show and tell&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz: API and R API packages on the example of XRONOS
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.xronos.ch">https://www.xronos.ch&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>R package: &lt;a href="https://github.com/xronos-ch/xronos.R">https://github.com/xronos-ch/xronos.R&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Useful in this context: &lt;a href="https://github.com/r-lib/vctrs">https://github.com/r-lib/vctrs&lt;/a> &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://github.com/r-lib/httr2">https://github.com/r-lib/httr2&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>James Allison will talk next month about R data parsing and transformation code he wrote to handle the output of a specific Agent-based modelling software tool&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>11th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-09-03/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-09-03/</guid><description>&lt;p>6 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zack Batist already sent out an invitation to the Google calendar on the mailing list. Everybody has read permissions to embed the calendar with their own ones, but only explicitly approved SIG members will get editing permissions to prevent abuse. Zack manages the permissions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We postponed the discussion about moving the meeting timeslot once more. If somebody is affected and thus can&amp;rsquo;t raise the issue in the meeting, please make us aware on the mailing list or the slack channel&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are a number of interesting, upcoming conferences/meetings:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>10th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-08-06/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-08-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>4 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The steering committee election cycle was set to two years with a three month overlap period. The next election will therefore be in October 2022&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &amp;ldquo;How to become a SIG SSLA member&amp;rdquo; document discussed in the last meeting is online now: &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/documents/becoming_a_member">https://sslarch.github.io/documents/becoming_a_member&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As an experiment we introduce a new recurring point of order &amp;ldquo;Show and tell&amp;rdquo; for our monthly meetings, that replaces/enhances &amp;ldquo;Open exchange about activities and software updates&amp;rdquo;. 1-2 volunteers show some interesting and preferably unpolished work-in-progress/tech wizardry in slots of 5 to 15 minutes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We now have a common google calendar, to share events relevant for all SIG members: &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/3dLYnoP1ywI">https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/3dLYnoP1ywI&lt;/a> (Members of the mailing list should already be able to edit it)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For many SIG members it might be better/indifferent to move the meeting timeslot by one hour. We should discuss this in the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>EAA2021: Martin Hinz prepared a useful list of sessions that focus on quantitative apporaches and computer applications (CfP is closed, though)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>16 “Economic Archaeology” and Quantitative Approaches – Measuring the Variations in Production and Consumption from Archaeological Data, 8 Sep 9:00 ‐ 13:00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>130 BIG‐BIO: Opportunities and Challenges of BIG Data with a Focus on BIO‐Archaeology, 7 Sep 14:30 ‐ 18:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>235 Is Machine Learning in Archaeology Fact or Fiction?, 10 Sep 9:00 ‐ 11:00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>267 History of Measuring and Calculations in Archaeology, 8 Sep 9:00 ‐ 13:00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>269 Between Variability and Singularity: Crossing Theoretical, Qualitative and Computer‐based Approaches to Types and Typologies in Archaeology [PaM], 10 Sep 9:00 ‐ 16:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>297 Modelling Complexity: Past Interactions between People, Climate and Environment [PaM], 11 Sep 9:00 ‐ 16:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>382 From the Field to the Computer. The Validity of Quantitative Methods Regarding the Quality of Archaeological Data, 11 Sep 14:30 ‐ 18:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>445 Digital Methods and Typology: New Horizons, 8 Sep 9:00 ‐ 13:00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>487 A network for agent‐based modelling of socio‐ecological systems in Archaeology (NASA), 9 Sep 9:00 ‐ 16:30&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="sig-activities">SIG activities&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Conference list&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>9th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-07-02/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-07-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>13 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-matters">Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Duration of the SIG SSLA steering committee election cycle
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We did not make a decision about this when we elected the commitee&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The members present in this meeting have no strong opinion about the matter&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ideally the full committee would not be replaced at once. Instead a certain overlap of members should uphold continuity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The current committee (Martin Hinz, Sophie Schmidt, Clemens Schmid) will prepare a suggestion for the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;How to join&amp;rdquo; instructions
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz prepared a guide with steps for new members to formally join the SIG&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Everybody liked it - except for the name &amp;ldquo;Boarding guide&amp;rdquo;, which should be changed (according to the native speakers)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A link to the document can be found in the Slack channel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The document is available for review until 2021-07-08. Then the committee will publish it on the website&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>More ideas to welcome new members
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Automatically invite people joining the mailing list to the Slack workspace&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A &amp;ldquo;Welcome officer&amp;rdquo; could handle these duties (volunteers wanted!)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The self introduction on Slack could be formalized with a template, e.g.:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>* Name: zack
* Pronouns: he/him
* Year Started at iSchool: 2016
* Research: archaeological databases, interdisciplinary collaboration, open data
* Academic Background: interdisciplinary studies (carleton), anthropology (mcmaster)
* Ask Me About: bad sci-fi, old movies, my cats
* Other Roles at the iSchool/UofT:
* Learn More Here: zackbatist.github.io, twitter.com/mtl_zack
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>CAA2021 debriefing&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tools for the Revolution: developing packages for scientific programming in archaeology</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2021_session/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2021_session/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://2021.caaconference.org/programme/">2021-06-16, 09:50–12:20&lt;/a> (UTC)&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Online, Room S (morning), Room P (afternoon)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The increasing use of scientific programming languages (e.g. R or Python) is transforming the practice of quantitative archaeology. This “tool-driven revolution” (Schmidt and Marwick 2020) promises to greatly improve the accessibility, power, and reproducibility of computational analyses. It is a core component of the “Third Science Revolution” (Kristiansen 2014), which has major theoretical and practical implications for the discipline of archaeology as a whole.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Developing R packages</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2021_workshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2021_workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> 2021-06-14&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A growing number of researchers use the scripting language R (R Core Team 2020) for scientific data analysis. Many organise their code in scripts and functions to perform sequences of data manipulation, statistics and visualisation. Sometimes these workflows gain in complexity and it becomes feasible to outsource core components into a dedicated R package. Packages are one of the best ways to make R code reproducible as they provide a well established structure to share functions, data and their documentation with other R-users. The vast numbers of packages by diverse developers on the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) indicate their popularity in the scientific community and they could very well become a pillar of scientific progress in archaeology (Schmidt and Marwick 2020). Indeed more and more packages are also being developed by and for archaeologists (e.g. &lt;a href="http://open-archaeo.info">http://open-archaeo.info&lt;/a>).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>8th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-06-04/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-06-04/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="caa2021">CAA2021&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Annual general meeting
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>As every year the CAA conference will feature the society&amp;rsquo;s AGM&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The SIG-SSLA will have to give a short report&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt will take over this duty&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Session S17
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Everything is well prepared&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe updated the homepage accordingly: &lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/sessioni">https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/sessioni&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The paper abstracts are available in the Github Repo: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_packages/tree/main/papers">https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_packages/tree/main/papers&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitter
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG account team will try to be very active by
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>life-tweeting sessions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>amplifying the voices of active community members&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A useful addition to the toolset might be tweetdeck: &lt;a href="https://tweetdeck.twitter.com">https://tweetdeck.twitter.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Workshop
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt, Petr Pajdla and Clemens Schmid prepared a program&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slides and excersises are already available here: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_Rpackage_workshop">https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_Rpackage_workshop&lt;/a> (in prep)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The members participating in this meeting had various detailed comments&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="non-caa-topics">Non-CAA topics&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG should actively try to attract a more diverse set of members - personal contacts and invitation might be a powerful medium to achieve this&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New, interesting papers:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2021.105413">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jas.2021.105413&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0251695">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0251695&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-friday-july-2-2021">Next meeting: Friday, July 2, 2021&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>7th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-05-14/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-05-14/</guid><description>&lt;p>6 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter account &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CAA_SSLA">@CAA-SSLA&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Is still very actively maintained&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Twitter subcommittee will have another organisational meeting soon&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As usual everybody is invited to join (contact via Slack channel)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slack workspace &lt;a href="sslarchworkspace.slack.com">sslarch&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There is not too much activity in the open channels, but many use the workspace for peer-to-peer communcation or discussions among smaller groups&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2021
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The current conference schedule has some drawbacks - we hope for an updated version that does not split our &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_packages">S17&lt;/a> over two days&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Workshop &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/caa2021_Rpackage_workshop">S31&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt, Petr Pajdla and Clemens Schmid will soon meet to define the exact outline of the workshop&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Multiple other SIG members offered to join the workshop as helpers and participants&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Extension &lt;a href="https://open-archaeo.info/">OpenArchaeo&lt;/a> [SIG Project]&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>6th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-04-09/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-04-09/</guid><description>&lt;p>12 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="agenda">Agenda&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Organisational matters
1.1. Update on the Twitter activities
1.2. Website update&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions
2.1. news on the two sessions at CAA international&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Open exchange about activities and software updates
3.1. Little minions @SSLA
3.2 new developments / tools etc
3.3 news on the working group Ordination and chronology ?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any other business?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="1-organisational-matters">1. Organisational matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="11-twitter">1.1 Twitter&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>everything&amp;rsquo;s running smooth&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aim to be locus of discussion is met&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martin, Sophie and Zack prepare tweets&lt;/li>
&lt;li>everyone: please join in creating content: links, ideas, things to share, what ever you come up with! &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; please share with Martin, Zack or Sophie&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="12-website">1.2 website&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joe Roe&amp;rsquo;s update has been merged&lt;/li>
&lt;li>everything is functional&lt;/li>
&lt;li>some minor tweaks can still be added&lt;/li>
&lt;li>main purpose of switching was to facilitate adding and updating content&lt;/li>
&lt;li>anyone can join in improving: fork and make a pull request!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="2-upcoming-conference">2. Upcoming Conference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA 2021: workshop s31
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>10 members&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Petr, Clemens and Sophie developed a rough outline which will be fleshed out further&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CAA 2021: theoretical session s17
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>several submissions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>review is in progress&lt;/li>
&lt;li>will link nicely to workshop&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="3-open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">3. Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="31-little-minions-httplittleminionslink">3.1. Little Minions, &lt;a href="http://littleminions.link/">http://littleminions.link/&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>working group:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-03-05/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-03-05/</guid><description>&lt;p>7 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter account update
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>According to the plans made during the last meeting, the twitter team followed a more strategic approach this month&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This increased both activity and interaction with followers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The plan for the next months can be summarised as: More engagement and less promotion to act less as entertainers and more like moderators (for meaningful user-user interaction)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This will also include cooperation with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Rchaeology1">https://twitter.com/Rchaeology1&lt;/a>, who is working on a twitter list of archaeologists using R&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Update of the homepage
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joe did further work on the homepage frontend&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The changes could be merged into the master branch immediately&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some details could be cleaned out in a group effort after this merge&lt;/li>
&lt;li>State of the discussion: &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/sslarch.github.io/issues/9">https://github.com/sslarch/sslarch.github.io/issues/9&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mailinglist
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joining the google mailinglist required confirmation by administrators until now&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We decided to abolish this to further lower the threshold of joining the group&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Meeting announcements
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>To make the meetings more visible, they should be announced in the future not only on the mailinglist, but also on slack and twitter&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2021
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Both our session and our workshop only have 5 submissions right now, but we know of multiple more submissions to be handed in before the deadline (12th March 2021, 23:59 GMT)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The group should again invite to both sessions on all available channels&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Providing the workshop behind the registration &amp;ldquo;paywall&amp;rdquo; of CAA2021 is not ideal, and we would like to share the material in an open context in the future&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ordination and chronology
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz would like to establish a small working group to discuss method development in that domain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Resources: (as spontaneously suggested by the group)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SPARTAAS R package: Statistical pattern recognition and dating using archaeological artefacts assemblages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brunner et al. (2020) Central European Early Bronze Age chronology revisited: A Bayesian examination of large-scale radiocarbon dating. PLOS ONE 15(12): e0243719. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0243719">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0243719&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ortman, Scott 2016. Uniform Probability Density Analysis and Population History in the Northern Rio Grande. Journal of Archaeological Method and Theory 23:95–12&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ortman et al. 2007 EMPIRICAL BAYESIAN METHODS FOR ARCHAEOLOGICAL SURVEY DATA: AN APPLICATION FROM THE MESA VERDE REGION. American Antiquity, 72(2), 2007, pp. 241-272&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Krauß et al. 2017. “Chronology and Development of the Chalcolithic Necropolis of Varna I”. Documenta Praehistorica 44 (December), 282-305. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.4312/dp.44.17">https://doi.org/10.4312/dp.44.17&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A new paper about software review in archaeology was pre-published recently
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Review of archaeological software: Recommendations for the review of archaeological research software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.dguf.de/fileadmin/AI/archinf-ev_homburg-etal_english.pdf">https://www.dguf.de/fileadmin/AI/archinf-ev_homburg-etal_english.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-friday-april-9-2021">Next meeting: Friday, April 9, 2021&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The executive committee invited the &amp;ldquo;Little minions&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="http://littleminions.link">http://littleminions.link&lt;/a>) group to join the next meeting and present their goals and vision&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>4th regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-02-02/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-02-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>8 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter account experiences
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>After an initial peak of activity the number of tweets and retweets is now slowly dying down. But we have 217 followers!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Everybody is very much invited to highlight observations that could be commented on or retweeted on the respective slack channel or the etherpad platform (&lt;a href="https://etherpad.wikimedia.org/p/ssla-tweets">https://etherpad.wikimedia.org/p/ssla-tweets&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The twitter team considers prescheduling regular tweets e.g. based on open-archeo (&lt;a href="https://github.com/zackbatist/open-archaeo">https://github.com/zackbatist/open-archaeo&lt;/a>) or the ctv-archaeology (&lt;a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology">https://github.com/benmarwick/ctv-archaeology&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Update of the homepage
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joe Roe proposed an alternative setup with hugo&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This setup is superior in terms of accessability for the disabled and has other technical advantages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vote to switch to the new setup: 8/8 Yes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe will prepare the switch with a PR to the website repository&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2021 Workshop
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt, Petr Pajdla and Clemens Schmid have prepared a general outline and the group agrees with it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The group highlights the importance of Git+Github, but agrees that it is going beyond the scope of this workshop. Collaborative work on code should be a topic for a workshop in the future&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>List of upcoming conferences
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz prepared a prototype here: &lt;a href="https://martinhinz.github.io/ssla_conf_list">https://martinhinz.github.io/ssla_conf_list&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He will integrated this into the main website via PR at some point&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>List of teaching materials
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This does not exist yet, but could be prepared in the future and would then be integrated into the website just as the list of conferences&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Upcoming talk at the Archaeological Information Interest Group: Building ARCS - The Archaeology Resource Cataloging System (&lt;a href="https://utoronto.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZAof--hqzMiGNbmOi73WFet-G_cd_BgAJgo">https://utoronto.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZAof--hqzMiGNbmOi73WFet-G_cd_BgAJgo&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-friday-march-5-2021">Next meeting: Friday, March 5, 2021&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>3rd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-01-05/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2021-01-05/</guid><description>&lt;p>9(+1?) ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter account
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>@SIG_SSLA &amp;lt;- follow me on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CAA_SSLA">https://twitter.com/CAA_SSLA&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The (first) twitter crew consists of the following members: Sophie Schmidt, Zack Batist, Martin Hinz&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The crew shares the password and is actively using the account according to our twitter guidelines (&lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/sslarch.github.io/blob/master/twitter_guidelines.md">https://github.com/sslarch/sslarch.github.io/blob/master/twitter_guidelines.md&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Input for the twitter channel can be shared on the respective Slack channel&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Experiences and opinions on Slack
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Everybody seems to be happy with the chat&amp;rsquo;s setup for now&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Logo
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Final poll among the most popular drafts
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>3: I&lt;/li>
&lt;li>6: II&lt;/li>
&lt;li>7: IIII &amp;lt;- !&lt;/li>
&lt;li>9: I&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Logo number 7 of the draft collection becomes the new SIG-SSLA logo&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens Schmid will clean up the logo repository (&lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/logo">https://github.com/sslarch/logo&lt;/a>) and prepare rendered versions for easy use&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2021 Workshop
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie, Petr and Clemens submitted a workshop as a type &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; session&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The interaction of the two sessions could be very interesting: The workshop can prepare or work with important concepts discussed in the second session&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any other conferences or meetings?
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>EAA2021: Call for sessions is open. There should be some CAA@EAA sessions that could be interesting for your papers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EAA could generally be a worthwile target for a future session organised by the SIG SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reproducible Quantitative Research in Archaeology: Doing Open Science Archaeology (using R) - Ben Marwick, David Matzig, Felix Riede, Sophie Schmidt Sophie (&lt;a href="https://www.hf.uio.no/iakh/english/research/dialogues-with-the-past/courses/reproducible-quantitative-research-in-archaeology-.html">https://www.hf.uio.no/iakh/english/research/dialogues-with-the-past/courses/reproducible-quantitative-research-in-archaeology-.html&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Winter School: R for Archaeologists - Francesco Carrer, Joe Row (&lt;a href="http://www.mappaproject.org/r4rchaeologists/">http://www.mappaproject.org/r4rchaeologists/&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The World Archaeological Congress (&lt;a href="https://www.wac-9.org/">https://www.wac-9.org/&lt;/a>) was postponed (Covid-19)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>OpenArchao (&lt;a href="https://open-archaeo.info/">https://open-archaeo.info/&lt;/a>) was greatly improved thanks to Joe Roe and Zack Batist. The data needs constant updating though - everybody can join here!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Similar to OpenArchaeo, the SIG-SSLA could provide an open repository for conferences and workshops. Martin Hinz will come up with an implementation idea for the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Uncommented: &lt;a href="https://merely-useful.github.io/py-rse/index.html">https://merely-useful.github.io/py-rse/index.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some open discussion about new developments regarding spatial data manipulation in R
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>stars package: spatiotemporal data handling with potentially interesting features for archaeology (&lt;a href="https://r-spatial.github.io/stars">https://r-spatial.github.io/stars&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>terra package: the future replacement of the raster package? (&lt;a href="https://github.com/rspatial/terra">https://github.com/rspatial/terra&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-february-2-2021">Next meeting: February 2, 2021&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>2nd regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-12-01/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-12-01/</guid><description>&lt;p>9 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter (some of these suggestions could become part of our Twitter guidelines)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The account can be set up and should have the name CAA-SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Content collection can happen on our group chat&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The account should focus on archaeology and not so much on general developments in the scripting languages world&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Solid, hearty, high quality tweets should dominate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Scheduling posts before posting and weekly/monthly collection posts may be powerful tools to increase impact&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We should post with one or multiple dedicated hashtags to allow for searching and filtering&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Regular tweets are better than random bursts of activity with weeks of silence in between&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Logo
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There are different preferences in the group&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We will organise a ranked poll to decide&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The winner of this survey will be announced at the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Group chat software
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Each system has clear advantages and disadvantages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For now we will set up a Slack channel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Later we want to change to something more FOSS&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-conferences-meetings-and-sessions">Upcoming conferences, meetings and sessions&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>CAA2021
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The SIG session &amp;ldquo;Tools for the Revolution: developing packages for scientific programming in archaeology&amp;rdquo; by Joe Roe, Martin Hinz and Clemens Schmid was submitted&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We did not discuss the planned, accompanying workshop&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="open-exchange-about-activities-and-software-updates">Open exchange about activities and software updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zack Batist: OpenArchaeo Update - &lt;a href="https://open-archaeo.info/">https://open-archaeo.info/&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ideas: Github integration, improved segmentation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The work on this list could become a collaborative project for the SIG SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joseph Lewis: Work on a new package to prepare high resolution topographic data for Italy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens: Exciting new version of magrittr
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2020/11/magrittr-2-0-is-here/">https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2020/11/magrittr-2-0-is-here/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>|&amp;gt; to be included as a &amp;ldquo;base&amp;rdquo; piping operator in an upcoming version of R&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Joe Roe: Mapping of TFQAR to R solutions - &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar">https://github.com/sslarch/tfqar&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Completing this list and bridging gaps between the tools could as well be a project for the SIG SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist: Invitation to participate in the colloquium of the Archaeological Information Interest Group of Toronto University
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/archaeological-information-interest-group">https://groups.google.com/g/archaeological-information-interest-group&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="next-meeting-january-5-2021">Next meeting: January 5, 2021&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>1st regular meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-11-03/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-11-03/</guid><description>&lt;p>11 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="organisational-issues">Organisational issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Members list on sslarch.github.io
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>fine like it is, good to see so many people there&lt;/li>
&lt;li>new members can add themselfes to the list with a Pull Request against the homepage repository&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitter
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a Twitter account would allow for better communication with non-members and official endorsements of strategic partners, e.g. other Special interest groups&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sophie and Zack will prepare a draft for a guidelines/code of conduct document how to handle the twitter account and present the result at the next meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Logo
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>collection of drafts at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/logo">https://github.com/sslarch/logo&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>redesign contest until the next meeting - submissions can be submitted directly to the repository&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Official email account
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>the SIG got an official email address from CAA&lt;/li>
&lt;li>it redirects to Martins mail address&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Chat software
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>in the future it might be useful to establish a group chat for the SIG&lt;/li>
&lt;li>so far it&amp;rsquo;s unclear which tool fits best: Slack, Discord, Gitter, Rocket.chat, &amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="news-from-the-scripting-languages-world-clemens">News from the scripting languages world (Clemens)&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New R version 4.0.3 (2020-10-10): &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/doc/manuals/r-release/NEWS.html">https://cran.r-project.org/doc/manuals/r-release/NEWS.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New Python version 3.9.0 (2020-10-05): &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-390/">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-390/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>GIS map making challenge: &lt;a href="https://www.gislounge.com/november-map-challenge/">https://www.gislounge.com/november-map-challenge/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New interesting R packages and package versions:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Spell checking: &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/spelling">https://github.com/ropensci/spelling&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixing coordinates: &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/parzer">https://github.com/ropensci/parzer&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/CoordinateCleaner">https://github.com/ropensci/CoordinateCleaner&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>WKT parsing: &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/wellknown">https://github.com/ropensci/wellknown&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fulltext search in published papers: &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/fulltext">https://github.com/ropensci/fulltext&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>JSON parsing: &lt;a href="https://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/rcpp.simdjson.html">https://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/rcpp.simdjson.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Unit tests: &lt;a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2020/10/testthat-3-0-0/">https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2020/10/testthat-3-0-0/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ODBC database interface: &lt;a href="https://github.com/r-dbi/odbc/releases/tag/v1.3.0">https://github.com/r-dbi/odbc/releases/tag/v1.3.0&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fast in-memory data manipulation: &lt;a href="https://arrow.apache.org/docs/r/index.html">https://arrow.apache.org/docs/r/index.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New open Books
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>R Shiny web development: &lt;a href="https://mastering-shiny.org">https://mastering-shiny.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>R Javascript integration: &lt;a href="https://book.javascript-for-r.com">https://book.javascript-for-r.com&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved Python interpreter now available in R-Studio: &lt;a href="https://blog.rstudio.com/2020/10/07/rstudio-v1-4-preview-python-support">https://blog.rstudio.com/2020/10/07/rstudio-v1-4-preview-python-support&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="caa-2021">CAA 2021&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Software package (R, Python, etc.) development session + introductory workshop: &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/Fz0PKtbFFAE">https://groups.google.com/g/scientific-scripting-languages-in-archaeology/c/Fz0PKtbFFAE&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Session: Joe, Martin, Clemens (Joe comes up with an abstract proposal)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Workshop: Sophie, Petr, (Clemens)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="practical-implementation-dissemination-of-teaching-material">Practical implementation dissemination of teaching material&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Open teaching material for archaeology: &lt;a href="https://www.archaeopress.com/ArchaeopressShop/Public/displayProductDetail.asp?id=%7B48586A9F-7C7A-4840-97AD-3C33D17D6E2A%7D">https://www.archaeopress.com/ArchaeopressShop/Public/displayProductDetail.asp?id=%7B48586A9F-7C7A-4840-97AD-3C33D17D6E2A%7D&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Inaugural meeting</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-10-06/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-10-06/</guid><description>&lt;p>14 ppl attended&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Voting was done using directpoll.com&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="report-of-recent-developments--5-min">Report of recent developments (~ 5 min)&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Approval by the CAA 2020-08-26&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provisional Transition Steering Committee (SC) of SIG-SSLA
2020-09-01 - Protocol online (&lt;a href="https://sslarch.github.io/protocols/2020-09-01.txt">https://sslarch.github.io/protocols/2020-09-01.txt&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Announcement in German Scientific Newsletter
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>any other members that know similar newsletters? -&amp;gt; please tell us so we can announce the SIG there too&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="collect-suggestions-and-ideas-from-members">Collect suggestions and ideas from members&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A running list of interesting projects and packages will be published on Github (Zack Batist)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A monthly (virtual) meeting to report on (Clemens Schmid)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>current developments in SSLA in archaeology&lt;/li>
&lt;li>talk about new versions, new packages, new libraries, version updates&lt;/li>
&lt;li>field is not that large, so we could create an overview of that&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Growth and diversity of the group (Ben Marwick, Martin Hinz)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>growth of the group - introduce members to SSLA by creating semi-formal cooperations with other groups&lt;/li>
&lt;li>society of archaeological sciences has connections to society of black archaeologists. smth. similar in Europe?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we should include ppl from Asia, global South etc!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Teaching and dissemination (Ben Marwick, Dirk Seidensticker, Martin Hinz, Jesse Wolfhagen)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>teaching is important and part of the statement already up on our website.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>platform for teaching tools? Provide things for new members, not just keeping ourselves up to date&lt;/li>
&lt;li>create groups that are focused on creating teaching material for specific SSLA&lt;/li>
&lt;li>first step: collect teaching material. Hub for all tutorials that are already there&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Minimal Standards and Best Practises (Ben Marwick, Jesse Wolfhagen, Martin Hinz)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>statement of minimum standards?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we could be an authority what should be taught at least? 10 things everyone should know?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>best practices? What makes scripts reproducible? what would you like to see as a reviewer?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>style guides? dependant on language - collect these and present them&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Practical implementation, Priorisation and Schedule (Clemens Schmid, Sophie Schmidt, Martin Hinz)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>ambitious goals for later. let&amp;rsquo;s start with &amp;ldquo;smaller achivable goals&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>collect the ideas in the e-mail-list. maybe create a thread there&lt;/li>
&lt;li>talk about ideas and prioritise at meetings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>explore possibilities to use github tools for task management&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="set-the-modus-operandi-monthly-meetings">Set the modus operandi (Monthly Meetings)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The plan: These regular meetings should be held monthly and should last about 1 hour. Current developments in the field of scripting languages should be briefly presented and discussed. Extensive presentations ala conference contribution should be avoided.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Meeting of the Provisional Steering Committee</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-09-01/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2020-09-01/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="participants">Participants:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sophie Schmidt&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zack Batist&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clemens Schmid&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martin Hinz&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="activities-currently-necessary">Activities currently necessary:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Information mail via the mailing list&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Organise an inaugural meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Establish regular meetings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Outreach&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="inaugural-meeting">inaugural meeting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The inaugural meeting should be the kick-off for regular meetings (see below).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>agenda:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Report of recent developments&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Collect suggestions and ideas from members&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Set the modus operandi&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Present potential candidates for the SC&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Election of the Steering Committee&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Positions to be filled are:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hackathon II – Unconference!</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2020_session/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2020_session/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update: As CAA2020 is &lt;a href="https://caa-international.org/2020/06/11/caa-2020-cancelled/">not going to take place&lt;/a> this session will not happen either. We will think about the concept and may resubmit for CAA 2021.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Pre-session discussion:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/sslarch/caa2020_hackathon/issues">https://github.com/sslarch/caa2020_hackathon/issues&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Scientific scripting languages are a very powerful tool for scientists to translate research questions and quantitative analysis into a machine-readable, executable and thus reproducible form. In order to promote and support their dissemination to the archaeological community, we have de facto established the Special Interest Group for Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology at CAA2019 in Krakow. To celebrate the de jure affiliation of this SIG to the CAA organization in 2020, this session will provide an open hackerspace for users of scripting languages.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CAA2019 Roundtable Discussion</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2019-04-24/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/minutes/2019-04-24/</guid><description>&lt;p>Introductory Statements&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Martin Hinz: Stay DRY! Why scientific scripting speeds up research, fosters more interesting science and helps save taxpayers money.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lizzy Scholtus: Scripting languages community: an important tool to develop the existence of these techniques&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joe Roe: The boundary between &amp;ldquo;scientific programming&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;software development&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Iza Romanowska: Who are Research Software Engineers and why should we care?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Clemens Schmid: (Don&amp;rsquo;t Fear) The Reaper. A SIG as long term software maintenance network?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology – Limits and Opportunities of Open Research</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2019_roundtable/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2019_roundtable/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> 2019/04/24, 16:00-18:00&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Auditorium Maximum of the Jagiellonian University, Kraków, seminar room, level 2
&lt;a href="protocols/2019-04-24.txt">&lt;strong>Here you may find the protocol&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="discussants">Discussants&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/martinusrihhi">Martin Hinz&lt;/a> (University of Bern)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/joeroe90">Joe Roe&lt;/a> (University of Copenhagen)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/iza_romanowska">Iza Romanowska&lt;/a> (Barcelona Supercomputing Center)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/idhrenil">Sophie Schmidt&lt;/a> (University of Cologne)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nevromecs">Clemens Schmid&lt;/a> (Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum Mainz)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/scholtuslizzie">Lizzie Scholtus&lt;/a> (University of Strasbourg)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At last year&amp;rsquo;s CAA, during the session on R in Archaeology, a suggestion was made to set up a Special Interest Group on Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology (SIG SSLA). We would like to comply with this proposal at this year&amp;rsquo;s CAA. We would also like to take advantage of the forum to discuss the SIG&amp;rsquo;s goals and agenda in a round table.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hackathon I – Can you code this?</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2019_workshop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/caa2019_workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>When:&lt;/strong> 2019/04/23&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Where:&lt;/strong> Auditorium Maximum of the Jagiellonian University&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In general, scientific scripting languages are the best interface for archaeologists to translate research questions into a machine-readable and executable form for quantitative analysis. For every step of data processing – data acquisition, analysis and presentation – there are high-quality software frameworks that enable fast, elegant, human-readable and reproducible coding. And yet, script languages are still not widely used! One of the main reason for this is the often steep learning curve. An important goal of the proposed Special Interest Group on Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology (SIG SSLA) is to provide guidance on how to overcome this obstacle.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Statement of purpose</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/about/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="sig-ssla">SIG SSLA&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The purpose of the &lt;a href="http://caa-international.org/special-interest-groups/">CAA Special Interest Group&lt;/a> &lt;strong>Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology&lt;/strong> is to promote the widespread implementation of computer scripts in archaeology. We will provide an exchange platform for scientists in and around archaeology who use scripting languages to conduct major or minor parts of their research. Scripts are computer programs that automate the execution of various kinds of tasks and are typically used by scientists to process and visualize information in ways that are amenable to the principles of open research. The purpose of this SIG is to help foster the growing community of archaeologists who increasingly use scientific scripting languages to pursue archaeological interests.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Andrea Titolo</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Ben Marwick</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Bjørn Peare Bartholdy</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>David N. Matzig</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Dirk Seidensticker</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Dries Daems</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Florian Thiery</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Francisco Javier Luengo Gutiérrez</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>How to join the SIG SSLA?</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/becoming_a_member/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/becoming_a_member/</guid><description>&lt;p>So, you want to become a member of the CAA Special Interest Group for Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology? You have questions about the qualifications you need? You want to know how to become a member? Wondering what the benefits are? Ask no more! Here are the answers you&amp;rsquo;ve been looking for.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-needed-to-become-a-member">What is needed to become a member&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As for the prerequisites, there are really none, except an interest in advancing transparency in archaeological research through both human and machine-readable computer programs. Whether you are already an experienced programmer in this field, or you are just starting out, it does not matter. Our group aims to provide an inclusive forum for exchange. Furthermore, we have made it our task to spread the knowledge about the possibilities and advantages of scripts over point and click software for scientific work and to establish it in a broad user group. Therefore, we are happy about every new member and hope that you will enrich us with your input and questions. To become a member of the Special Interest Group, you also do not have to be necessarily a member of CAA as such.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>James Allison</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Joe Roe</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Joseph Lewis</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Letter to the members of the SIG</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/letter_members_bid/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/letter_members_bid/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dear colleagues,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You are receiving this message because you are listed on the mailing list as a potential member of a CAA Special Interest Group (SIG) &amp;lsquo;Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year at the CAA 2020 in Oxford we will submit a bid to have this group accepted as an official SIG of the CAA. In a preliminary enquiry to the CAA, we were told that we should illustrate in the bid that we already have support, preferably by compiling a list of archaeologists expressing their interest in the new SIG.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lisa Steinmann</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Miguel Carrero</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Mikel Díaz</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Peter Demján</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Petr Pajdla</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Sébastien Plutniak</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Special interest group proposal</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/caa_proposal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/caa_proposal/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dear honourable members of the CAA Steering Committee,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With this letter, we would like to express our intention to establish a &lt;strong>CAA Special Interest Group&lt;/strong> for &lt;strong>Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology (SIG-SSLA)&lt;/strong> under the auspices of the CAA. The idea for this SIG was developed in 2018 in a session on R as an archaeological tool. Out of this event and the resulting discussions, it was proposed to form such a Special Interest Group to create a permanent platform for the exchange and discussion of ideas and to develop the practical use of R for archaeological applications. After further discussions with colleagues, it became clear that it would be a good idea to extend the focus to all scientific script languages.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thomas Huet</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item><item><title>Twitter guidelines</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/twitter_guidelines/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/documents/twitter_guidelines/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="we-can-collect-here-what-we-would-like-to-use-twitter-for">We can collect here what we would like to use Twitter for&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>dissemination of new packages, releases etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>dissemination of actions planned by the SIG&lt;/li>
&lt;li>point of contact for outsiders&lt;/li>
&lt;li>amplify and support the work done by individuals and other collectives that relates to our core mission&lt;/li>
&lt;li>generally promote scientific computing as a cool thing to do 8-)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="curation">Curation&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>rolling by a team of volunteers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>gathering of ideas by all members of the SIG&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="rules">Rules&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>do not post or share harmful, offensive or illegal content, including that which is racist, homophobic, transphobic, sexist, ableist or which hatefully targets a religious group&lt;/li>
&lt;li>do not share personal information about any specific individual without their express consent (i.e. doxxing)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>do not post or link to pornography&lt;/li>
&lt;li>do not engage in pointless arguments or flamewars&lt;/li>
&lt;li>do not be a troll&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Zack Batist</title><link/><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid/><description/></item></channel></rss>