<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sessions on CAA/SSLA</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/</link><description>Recent content in Sessions on CAA/SSLA</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Session I</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/sessioni/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/sessioni/</guid><description>S17 Tools for the Revolution: developing packages for scientific programming in archaeology? Joe Roe, Martin Hinz, Clemens Schmid
Organisational information When: 2021-06-16, Details unkown Where: Online, Details unknown
Abstract The increasing use of scientific programming languages (e.g. R or Python) is transforming the practice of quantitative archaeology. This “tool-driven revolution” (Schmidt and Marwick 2020) promises to greatly improve the accessibility, power, and reproducibility of computational analyses. It is a core component of the “Third Science Revolution” (Kristiansen 2014), which has major theoretical and practical implications for the discipline of archaeology as a whole.</description></item><item><title>Workshop I</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/workshopi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/workshopi/</guid><description>S31 Workshop: Developing R packages? Sophie C. Schmidt, Petr Pajdla, Clemens Schmid
Organisational information When: 2021-06-14, Details unkown Where: Online, Details unknown
Abstract A growing number of researchers use the scripting language R (R Core Team 2020) for scientific data analysis. Many organise their code in scripts and functions to perform sequences of data manipulation, statistics and visualisation. Sometimes these workflows gain in complexity and it becomes feasible to outsource core components into a dedicated R package.</description></item><item><title>Hackathon II</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/hackathonii/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/hackathonii/</guid><description>S27 CAA Scripting Languages Hackathon II – Unconference! Clemens Schmid, Martin Hinz
Update: As CAA2020 is not going to take place this session will not happen either. We will think about the concept and may resubmit for CAA 2021.
Pre-session discussion: https://github.com/sslarch/caa2020_hackathon/issues
Abstract Scientific scripting languages are a very powerful tool for scientists to translate research questions and quantitative analysis into a machine-readable, executable and thus reproducible form. In order to promote and support their dissemination to the archaeological community, we have de facto established the Special Interest Group for Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology at CAA2019 in Krakow.</description></item><item><title>Roundtable</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/round_table/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/round_table/</guid><description>S03 Roundtable Scientific Scripting Languages in Archaeology - Limits and Opportunities of Open Research Martin Hinz, Clemens Schmid, Sophie Schmidt
Organisational information When: 2019/04/24, 16:00-18:00
Where: Auditorium Maximum of the Jagiellonian University, Kraków, seminar room, level 2 Here you may find the protocol
Discussants Martin Hinz (University of Bern)
Joe Roe (University of Copenhagen)
Iza Romanowska (Barcelona Supercomputing Center)
Sophie Schmidt (University of Cologne)
Clemens Schmid (Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum Mainz)
Lizzie Scholtus (University of Strasbourg)</description></item><item><title>Hackathon I</title><link>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/hackathon/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sslarch.github.io/sessions/hackathon/</guid><description>W4 CAA Scripting Languages Hackathon I – Can you code this? Clemens Schmid, Martin Hinz, Carolin Tietze
Organisational information When: 2019/04/23, Details unkown Where: Auditorium Maximum of the Jagiellonian University, Kraków, Details unknown
Abstract In general, scientific scripting languages are the best interface for archaeologists to translate research questions into a machine-readable and executable form for quantitative analysis. For every step of data processing – data acquisition, analysis and presentation – there are high-quality software frameworks that enable fast, elegant, human-readable and reproducible coding.</description></item></channel></rss>